<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Felmersham and Radwell</title>
                <title type="sub">1890-1965</title>
                <author>Robert Turner</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p part="N">Privately published. </p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <p part="N">Encoded from typescript manuscript</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main"><placeName ref="#pl:felmersham" instant="false"
                            full="yes">FELMERSHAM</placeName> AND <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                            >Radwell</placeName></titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="subtitle">1890-1965</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor>Robert Turner</docAuthor>
            </titlePage>
            <div type="preface" part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <pb n="1"/>
                <head>1965 - <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> AND
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName></head>
                <p part="N">In this book I have tried to outline the history of the two villages,
                    the best I can in the last 80 years up to and including 1965, with the help of
                    some of the elder people in the two villages.</p>
                <p part="N">There are things happened in the two villages that I know nothing about,
                    so please excuse me if I have not mentioned them, I hope that all who reads the
                    book will enjoy it, I have wrote it the best I can.</p>
                <byline>Robert Turner.</byline>
                <closer>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>THE GREEN,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>RADWELL,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                            <placeName ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName>.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <dateline>
                        <date when="1965-03" instant="false"> March 1965. </date>
                    </dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <p part="N">
                    <pb n="2"/> In this Book I am going to try and outline the history as far. as I
                    can in the villages of <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>
                    and <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>. From <date when="1890"
                        instant="false">1890</date> to <date when="1965" instant="false">1965</date>
                    there has been a lot of changes, in those years which I am going to try and
                    explain, which I hope will be interesting to read, in the village. </p>
                <p part="N"> In those days <persName ref="#pers-green-hh">the Squire</persName> was
                        <persName ref="#ps:green-hh">H. H. Green</persName> who lived at
                        <placeName>The Grange</placeName> and after his death it was taken over by
                        <persName ref="#ps:veils-richard">Richard Veils</persName>, which I
                    shall be writing about later on in the Book. </p>
                <p part="N"> First I would like to write about my own Family. My Mother was born at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> and lived in the
                    old <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> Manor House near
                    the <placeName ref="#pl:six-ringers-inn">Six Ringers</placeName> where the
                    new houses are being built today 1965. It is known as <placeName
                        ref="#pl:marriotts-close">Marriotts Close</placeName>. There was a
                    footpath in the field which came out opposite the Church. My Father used to use
                    that path when he went to work on the Railway. The Manor House was burned down,
                    my Mother used to tell us she lived there until she was married and then they
                    lived in the house where <persName ref="#ps:hulatt-george">Mr.</persName>
                    and <persName ref="#ps:hulatt-mrs">Mrs. George Hulatt</persName> lives
                    today. After then they bought the house up <placeName>Town Hot Lane</placeName>
                    and there they brought a lot of their big family up, which I will outline to
                    you. There was <num value="21">21</num> children in our family altogether and my
                    Mother and Father brought <num value="15">15</num> up, <num value="9">9</num>
                    boys and <num value="6">6</num> girls, the boys names were, <persName
                        ref="#ps:turner-albert">Albert</persName>, <persName
                        ref="#ps:turner-charles">Charles</persName>,
                        <persName>William</persName>, <persName>Arthur</persName>,
                        <persName>Frank</persName>, <persName>Jack</persName>,
                        <persName>Bert</persName>, <persName>Robert</persName> and
                        <persName>Fred</persName>, who was killed in the 1914-18 war. The girls was
                        <persName>Eliza</persName>, <persName>Minnie</persName>,
                        <persName>Dora</persName>, <persName>Ida</persName>,
                        <persName>Hetty</persName> and <persName>Sarah</persName>. </p>
                <p part="N"> My Father was born at <placeName>Campton</placeName> and in those days
                    he used to walk from <placeName>Campton</placeName> to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> which is about 15 miles, to
                    court my Mother, they used to tell us in those days, I wonder today if they
                    would do that to see their young lady? Of course there were no other transport,
                    bicycles were not then on the market, only the old Penny Farthing. </p>
                <p part="N"> I will now try and tell you about some of the things that used to
                    happen in the village in my boy days. The Squire and the Parson was the Leading
                    Light in those days and what they said was Law as far as it could be, so
                    everyone had to keep the right side as near as you could manage to do so. Of
                    course there was good times as well as bad times, we used to have to make our
                    own enjoyment which consisted a Reading Room in the Winter, and Cricket in the
                    Summer, which <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> always
                    had a cricket team, and then they used to fill their spare time in, when they
                    had any, in fishing. </p>
                <p part="N"> You would always see all the village mostly in their best clothes on
                    Sunday and the majority go to the Church, and the Squire <pb n="3"/> would be
                    there to see fair play. I remember the Squire fetching me out as we were
                    playing, I was on the end of a row and he got out of his pew and came down the
                    Church, and got hold of my left ear, and had me up to where his pew was, and
                    there I had to stand for the remainder of the Service. </p>
                <p part="N"> The Squire was a gentleman farmer and used to grow a lot of corn. You
                    could see stacks all along the fields and then in the winter time it would be
                    thrashed out and the straw etc. fed to the cattle. The Squire had several farms
                    he had land at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>, <placeName
                        ref="#pl:odell">Odell</placeName>, <placeName ref="#pl:bletsoe"
                        >Bletsoe</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#pl:grendon"
                        >Grendon</placeName>. He was a big sheep farmer and also kept some fine
                    bullocks. The sheep used to be fed on the swedes in the Winter and fatted up for
                    the Market. </p>
                <p part="N"> Of course in those days the work wall all done by horses there was no
                    tractors, the only machines was a Reaper Binder and Grass Cutter, and all the
                    corn and hay etc. was carted by the horse and cart or wagon. The Squire used to
                    keep about <num value="20">20</num> horses to do the work on the various farms.
                    He had 3 Horse Keepers and they used to fetch their horse in at <time
                        when="04:00:00" instant="false">4.O'clock in the morning</time> and bate
                    them ready to go out about <time when="06:30:00" instant="false">6.30</time> and
                    they would return home about <time when="14:30:00" instant="false">2.30</time>
                    for dinner. They only used to go out once a day until later on, they would come
                    in at <time when="10:00:00" instant="false">10.0 o'clock</time> and go out again
                    at <time when="14:00:00" instant="false">2.0</time> to work in the afternoon. It
                    was a hard day for horses and men in those days and not much at the end of the
                    week, the Squire used to pay 13/- a week and 1/- for Sundays when you had to go.
                    Then when wheat made £2 per cwt. he paid them 14/- per week so you see there was
                    not much to throw about in those days. Some of the farmers did not pay as much
                    as the Squire, it was round about 12/- per week. Of course there was beer for
                    the men at Manor for Thrashing, Drilling and various other jobs on the farm. The
                    Squire had a forman, his name was <persName ref="#ps:goodman-t">T.
                        Goodman</persName>, he was alright until he over- stepped the mark and did
                    not know what was his. He finished up with <date dur="P6M" instant="false">six
                        months</date> prison. The Foreman <persName ref="#ps:goodman-j">J.
                        Goodman</persName> used to live in the house where <persName
                        ref="#ps:hitchin">Mr. Hitchin</persName> lives and farms today. The men
                    and boys used to go for their orders at <time when="06:00:00" instant="false"
                        >6.0 o'clock</time> in the morn- ing and then they would go on their various
                    jobs set out for them and then on Saturday evenings they would have to go up to
                    the Foreman's house to get their weekly wages and some would go to the pub for
                    the evening to have a Sing Song and play darts and that's how the life in the
                    village would go on week in and week out. </p>
                <p part="N"> On Good Friday you used to have to go to Church or you <pb n="4"/>
                    would lose your day's pay, unless you was ill. There was no work in Good Friday,
                    it was treated more or less as a Sunday in the village. The Squire used to go
                    round the farms with the Foreman,when he visited his farm at Odell he would go
                    in his carriage with his coachman and look round the cattle. There was a punt
                    across the river opposite the Grange which the men used to cross in to go to
                    work in the fields on the Odell side. The Squire would cross in the punt when he
                    wanted to see how the farming was going on. The punt was worked across the river
                    by a length of chain attached to both ends, so you could get across whichever
                    side the punt was and so the work went on in that way. </p>
                <p part="N"> The Squire used to have Shooting parties, they used to shoot in
                        <placeName ref="#pl:odell-wood">Odell Wood</placeName> and over the
                    various farms. There used to be a pack of Hare Hounds come to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>. <persName
                        ref="#ps:carpenter">Mr. Carpenter</persName> was the Huntsman and always
                    met at the Grange in the Morning, they used to hunt off the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell-road">Radwell Road</placeName> and round about until
                    lunch-time. There was Beer, Bread and Cheese if you wanted it and then after
                    lunch they would go up the <placeName ref="#pl:carlton-road">Carlton
                        Road</placeName> and you could stand on the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:carlton-road">Carlton Road</placeName> and if they did not catch
                    the Hare it would come back in the same field again where it started from. In
                    the later years <persName>Mr. Frank Green</persName> the son of the Squire had
                    his own pack of Hare Hounds and they were housed in the buildings and stables
                    where <persName>Mr. A. Odell</persName> lives today, and the bungalow was built
                    for his Stud Groom, <persName>Mr. Sidney Wall</persName>. They used to hunt the
                    Pack in those days in the village and elsewhere, so there was an active life in
                    the village. As there was a lot of Grooms in those days to look after the horses
                    as most of them used to go Hunting with the Oakley Hounds in the time of Witches
                    and Arkwright THE Ground which joins <persName instant="false" full="yes">Mr. A.
                        Odell's</persName> bungalow used to be used for washing the sheep before the
                    shearing began. They used to bring their sheep to be washed from other villages.
                    A stage was fixed out in the river and they used to throw the sheep in and other
                    men would be there with rubbers to wash the dust out of the wool, and I have
                    seen myself many a one swim across the river on the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> side, and that is how the
                    sheep used to be washed in those days. Of course they had to get permission off
                    the foreman before the farmers could bring their sheep to be washed. Most
                    farmers had a shepherd in those days, <persName>Mr. William Ashpole</persName>
                    was Shepherd for the Squire in those days. Of course it was a beer job and a lot
                    of that at times. </p>
                <p part="N"> So much for the sheep washing now I must see about the Ram Sale, which
                    used to be held in the village most years. They used to be a long time in
                    preparing the ram for sale. They used to get <pb n="5"/> them ready in
                        <placeName>Harvest Yard</placeName> opposite Mr. Church's farm yard which is
                    now built on. The Ram Sale used to be held in July and the Rams used to go all
                    over the Country. There was a big marquee and in the evening there was a smoking
                    concert and artist to entertain you. The people used to come from all the
                    villages round, the sale used to be held in the ground which is known as the
                    Hills along the side of the River off the <placeName ref="#pl:carlton-road"
                        >Carlton Road</placeName>. There was barrels of beer and bread and cheese as
                    much as you liked to drink. There was a man from Odell who,they tell me, had too
                    much and walked in the river and was drowned. His name was Kennedy, they tell
                    me. I have a strong suspicion that ended the Smoking Concert after that. </p>
                <p part="N">
                    <persName>Lord Alan Compton</persName> was M.P. at those time. There is one
                    thing when the Squire had a do it was a good one. I remember quite well the time
                    when the daughters used to be married. It was a free do for all the whole
                    villages of <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>. There was sports for
                    all to take part in if they wished to do so, and it was the West door that the
                    Wedding Couple used to use on these occasions. THE Bell used to Ring most of the
                    day, all the children used to have races, and the Squire used to have to watch
                    them. Also the Squire's whole family used to take an active part in the life of
                    the village. The Squire used to be a Timber Merchant and used to travel to
                        <placeName>London</placeName> for business purposes. He would go by train
                    from <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> Station, he would
                    go in his carriage and his Coachman would meet him at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> about 6.30 in the evening and
                    the people who was on the bridge when he came over would touch their hats at
                    him. He was what you would call a Country Gentleman and he was greatly missed
                    when he died in 1915. He was the last one buried in the Church. I myself was in
                        <placeName>France</placeName> in the 1914-18 war. <persName>Mr. Wm.
                        Hackney</persName> took over the Foreman's job after Mr. J. Goodman and
                    after the sale of the Squire's Estate, <persName>Mr. Wm. Hackney</persName> took
                    the farm over on his own and farmed there until <persName>Mr. L.
                        Church</persName> took over the farm and is still farming there today and
                    has bought the farm a few years .ago. </p>
                <p part="N"> Now I must try and outline the activities which have occured in the two
                    villages. Its nothing strange to seer women working in the fields today as this
                    used to go on years ago, but did not get much tor their work but they had to do
                    it to make end meet. After harvest you would see all the women and children in
                    the fields gleaning and this would be taken home and then afterwards the farmers
                    would have a day and thrash it out for them, and the corn would be ground into
                    flour and used in the winter to help <pb n="6"/> to feed the family and that
                    used to go on in most homes. It was also used to feed,the pig in the sty, and so
                    it carry on. Each family had a bit of allotment to grow their vegetables and so
                    help the weekly budget. Beer was 2d. a pint and cigarettes 5d. tobacco 2d and
                    3d.only. You could get 1/2 lb of sweets, if you had a penny you were well off.
                    In the pub, if you had what they called a latch lifter you was O.K. Some of the
                    men would have beer on tick till the end of the week and that is how things used
                    to go on in the village. I think there was a lot more beer drunk in those days.
                    In harvest time men would go in what they called their Month and you would get
                    double pay and you would get beer 3 to 4 times a day, you would go at 5.0
                    o'clock in the morning until 7.30 in the evening except when you were at cart
                    and then you used to carry on until it was dark, and after your month was up the
                    farmer would pay you an extra month pay which you would,if you were a good
                    husband,take it home and then your wife would take the children into <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> to fix them up for the winter and
                    this is how it went on each year. </p>
                <p> At Xmas time there was not many toys, perhaps you would get a Monkey on
                    a Stick, and a few sugar mice, and home-made sweets, a orange, nuts and dates,
                    of course you did hang your stocking up. and hope for the best. Today its a
                    different problem, they have a pillow-case to hang up now, and jolly good luck
                    to them, what a change there is in this last 50 years. No one would have
                    believed it 50 years ago. </p>
                <p part="N"> There was 4 farmers in the village, <persName>Squire Green</persName>,
                        <persName>Mr. Brooks</persName>, <persName>Mr. Flemings</persName>, and
                        <persName>Mr. Jack Thomas</persName>. There were also the small farmers re,
                        <persName>Charles Robinson</persName>, <persName>Charlie Cook</persName>, he
                    farmed at <placeName ref="#pl:hardwick-farm">Hardwick Farm</placeName>. The 4
                    farmers as I have mentioned above when the harvest came round they would try to
                    see who could finish Harvest Home first. The first one that finished would
                    collect all the children, men and women in the village, cut boughs from the
                    trees and then the horse, cart and wagons would go round the village loaded
                    singing, Holler Boy Holler Boy Harvest Home and not to forget to call for
                    refreshments at the various hotels in the village and what a night that was in
                    those days. Then after the Harvest Thanksgiving at the Church which was a big
                    occasion in those days and is so today, but I do not think in the same spirit as
                    it was in the old days. They would come for miles round, it would be told in the
                    village that it was the Harvest Thanksgiving at <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham"
                        >Pavenham</placeName>, Odell <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton
                        Ernest</placeName> or <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName>, and you would go, and of course you had to walk
                    there were no buses those days. The courting couples would attend and then it
                    was walk home, perhaps discussing your <pb n="7"/> future life and wedding day.
                    The couples used to generally pair, up from the other villages round, and as a
                    rule when a couple were married the bell would ring and the ringers would go to
                    the Bride's house for refreshments and then go back and give another peal on the
                    bells. Of course there were no Honeymoon those days there was not the money to
                    afford one because on the farms single men had 11/- per week and when they got
                    married their wages were rose to 12/- per week. So in those days when you took a
                    wife she was only worth 1/- what would the ladies of today say, that is one I
                    cannot answer. Well that is how the life in the village was in those good old
                    days, but as I said before there were good times as well as bad ones and these
                    always will be.</p>
                <p part="N"> There was always an Harvest Supper. The Squire would hold these in the
                        <placeName>Sun Club Room</placeName> and sometimes the Squire would come
                    down in the evening to celebrate and have a drink with his men. There was always
                    a few guests the foreman would invite and a jolly evening was spent with songs
                    and sometimes dancing. The Small Farmers would have a supper at their farmhouse
                    and that's how life went on in the village 60 years ago. Of course today in 1965
                    everything is done with machinery and there's not time to celebrate and it takes
                    7 days to do it. </p>
                <p part="N">It was in the old days that a good many jobs were done by hand. I have
                    been told that down in <placeName>Wolfsmead</placeName>, a field which farmed by
                    the Squire. There was 17 moving barley with syths and in the course of the day,
                        <persName>Fred Payne</persName> who lives at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> today fetched 17 gallon of
                    beer from <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> Pub, that was
                    beside what was allowed them for the day. <persName>Mr. J. Desborough</persName>
                    kept the Pub at the time, <persName>Mr. John Hulatt</persName> was one of the
                    Mowers and according to what I have been told there were none fit to drive a car
                    on that day. It was on those days when the Squire in his younger day and his
                    family were at home, the bell would be rung for dinner, so if any of the family
                    were about they knew it was time and the Squire were very strict about meals
                    times. The bell would be rung at 1.0 o'clock and 7.0 o'clock in the evening, for
                    both meals.</p>
                <p part="N">On Saturdays the large families, the Widows and Old Maids which there
                    was a few in those days could go to the Grange at 11 o'clock and would be given
                    a can of soup which the cook would give out to them and that would go on each
                    week. Then in October those that was in need of another blanket could have one
                    from the Grange. The <pb n="8"/> big families and old people used to have them,
                    and then at the end of March they were washed and taken back and fetched again
                    in October, and that is how the life went on in the village. It was no shame in
                    those days to accept charity.</p>
                <p part="N">The Squire at Xmas time would give all his employees a joint of Beef and
                    the others in the village would get a couple of rabbits and so on, so no-one
                    used to be without a Xmas Dinner.</p>
                <p part="N">The Coachman in my younger days was a man named <persName>Bob
                        Newton</persName> then after he left <persName>Mr. A. Ashpole</persName>
                    known as <persName>Bartney</persName> took the job on, and he was with the
                    Squire as Coachman until the Squire died in 1915.</p>
                <p part="N">I am now going to write about the various things that happened with
                    regard to the population of the village, there was some very large families in
                    those days. There was a family known as the <persName>Rust</persName>, which
                    there are some in the village this present day in 1965. The most outstanding as
                    far as I know was <persName>Ted Rust</persName>, who used to live in the house
                    that <persName>Mr. Fred Payne</persName> lives in today. They used to call him
                        <persName>Inkey Ted</persName>. He had a son which I knew quite well, and
                    his name was <persName>David Rust</persName>, and as far as I know he had 8
                    children, 5 boys and 3 girls. The names were <persName>George</persName>,
                        <persName>Arthur</persName>, <persName>Charles</persName>,
                        <persName>Tom</persName> and <persName>Ernest</persName>, and what lads they
                    was to be sure. They would crack a joke and I can assure you they would make a
                    cat laugh at their jokes. I think <persName>Charles</persName>, known as
                        <persName>Cunning</persName>, was the outstanding one of the 5,
                        <persName>George</persName> he died early in life, he used to work as far as
                    I know down on <placeName>Moorend Farm</placeName>, as a Shepherd. There was 3
                    daughters, <persName>Annie</persName>, <persName>Maude</persName> and
                        <persName>Mary</persName>. <persName>Annie</persName> married <persName>Mr.
                        C. Everest</persName> who lives at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> in the same house as he did 50 years ago, he will be
                    81 this year. Now at the present time his daughter and her husband are taken
                    over the house which I shall be writing about later on.
                        <persName>Maud</persName> the other daughter, the Mother of <persName>Mr.
                        Sid Lovell</persName>'s wife who live at <placeName ref="#pl:sun-inn">the
                        Sun</placeName> married <persName>Mr. Fred Payne</persName> who lives in the
                    house where <persName>Ted Rust</persName> lived. The youngest daughter married
                        <persName>Mr. A. Robinson</persName> of <placeName ref="#pl:harrold"
                        >Harrold</placeName>, and I am sorry to say that this family has all passed
                    on and I would like to add at this stage that they are all interned in
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham Church Yard</placeName> with
                    the exception of <persName>Mrs. Robinson</persName> who was interned in the
                    cemetery at <placeName ref="#pl:harrold">Harrold</placeName>, their Father,
                    Grandfather and many more of the <persName>Rust</persName> family are interned
                    in <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> Church Yard which I
                    think must be a record for so many relations.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr. G. Hulatt</persName> who was roadman in <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> had a family of 7 sons and 2
                    daughters and there is none of them living in the village today. <persName>Mr.
                        W. Hulatt</persName>, husband of <persName>Mrs, Hulatt</persName> who keep
                    the Post Office today died last year <date when="1964" instant="false"
                        >1964</date>. I shall be writing <pb n="9"/> more about the Post Office
                    later on.</p>
                <p part="N">Now I would like to write something about the
                        <persName>Gadsby</persName> family. <persName>Amos Gadsby</persName> was
                    Sexton at the Church for many years he was there at the time of the Vicar,
                        <persName>William Lathbridge</persName> and he used to be Gardener and
                    Handyman and take the Vicar out in a 4 wheel carriage.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Amos Gadsby</persName> had 8 children, 4 boys and 4 girls. One
                    of the girls married a man named <persName>Chapman</persName>, when the house
                    was sold which used to be known as The Old Reading Room, <persName>Mr.
                        Chapman</persName> bought it, he also bought the houses known as The Row,
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>. The house known
                    as The Reading Mr. Boness lives there today 1965. <persName>Mr.
                        Chapman</persName> turned the old house into a new one, he was a carpenter
                    and worked in <placeName>London</placeName> at this time, but after he made the
                    alterations he came there to live. He had two children,
                        <persName>Ruby</persName> and <persName>Percy</persName>.
                        <persName>Ruby</persName> married <persName>Mr. W. Wallenger</persName> who
                    was a Baker for many years at <placeName>Harrold</placeName> and his wife still
                    lives there. <persName>Percy</persName> lives at <placeName>London</placeName>
                    as far as I know. On the death of their Father the houses known as
                        <placeName>The Row</placeName>, <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> came over to <persName>Mrs. Wallenger</persName> and
                    the house where Boness lives came over to <persName>Percy</persName>. I cannot
                    say for sure if this is correct or not.</p>
                <p part="N">With regard to the others in the family the sons are all passed on but
                    there is as far as I know 3 daughters living at <placeName ref="#pl:clapham"
                        >Clapham</placeName>, <persName>Mrs. C. Tew</persName> is one who lives at
                    No. 8 Milton Road, <placeName ref="#pl:clapham">Clapham</placeName>. There is
                    several of Herbert's soils who live at <persName>Odell</persName> one is known
                    as Amos named after his Grandfather. The Gadsby's used to live in the house the
                    last one on the right hand side going to <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham"
                        >Pavenham</placeName>. This family was all for the Church and did some good
                    work to maintain it. I myself have always through my life been connected with
                    this family, we used to meet together at Xmas time. They 1ived at that time in
                    the house now where <persName>Mr. Bob Marsh</persName> lives today,
                        <persName>Mr. Bob Marsh</persName> came to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> to be Shepherd in February
                    1931 and he retired in 1958, he is now age 78. He lost his wife in 1945 and he
                    has one son and five daughters, <persName>Gladys</persName> one of the daughters
                    married <persName>Mr. Sam Lovell</persName> who at the present time is in the
                    building business with his two sons and will, in due course, be going back to
                    live in the house which his Father <persName>Thomas Lovell</persName> bought at
                    my Father's sale and where I was born on December 1st, 1890. <persName>Mr. Sara
                        Lovell</persName> took the house over after the death of his Father Thomas
                    Lovell, and is now making alterations to the old house.</p>
                <p part="N">I would like now to tell you something about the fire which occured in,
                    the village round about 60 year ago or thereabout. The building was at the time
                    of the fire rented by Mr. Riseley who used to be a Smallholder and used to have
                    land let out then as allotments up the <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook-road"
                        >Sharnbrook Road</placeName> known as <placeName ref="#pl:the-moors">the
                        Moors</placeName>. He used to take his <pb n="10"/> vegetables etc. to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:rushden">Rushden</placeName> to sell. On the night of
                    the fire it was rumoured in the village that someone, not known, had tried to
                    steal some of his apples etc. he used to sell, he used to grow strawberries on
                    his land up the <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook-road">Sharnbrook
                        Road</placeName>. The land belonged to the late <persName>Stilman
                        Gibbard</persName> on the night of the fire, it was between 11 and 12 and
                    what gave us the warning was the Bangers off of the Pantiles from the heat. The
                    Fire Engine which was kept at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName>, someone cycled to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> to summons the captain who
                    was I think <persName>George Newell</persName>, and he had to get in touch with
                    the other firemen and to make things better they had to get one of the late
                        <persName>John Thorn</persName>'s horses to drawn the fire engine to the
                    scene of the fire and perhaps it would be any- thing up to two hours before they
                    arrived and then the hose would be run out and then came the pumping operations
                    which would consist of men each side of the engine working the pumps On this
                    particular fire the hose was put down the well in the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sun-inn">Sun Inn</placeName> Yard which was emptied in due
                    course. The captain would come round and take your names and in due course you
                    would receive the sum of 2s. 6d. for your pumping operation. The fire engine
                    left round about 8.0 o'clock in the morning. After the fire <persName>Mr.
                        Riseley</persName> moved to <placeName ref="#pl:rushden"
                        >Rushden</placeName>, his son <persName>Durent</persName> married the
                    daughter of <persName>Mr. William Roberts</persName> who lived at the time in
                    the house which was occupied afterward by <persName>Mr, Jack
                    Ashpole</persName>.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr. D. Riseley</persName> and his wife went to Canada where
                    they are today according to the confirmation I have gathered off of their
                    relations. His wife is more or less an invalid, that is as far as I can go on
                    this subject.</p>
                <p part="N">I will now try to tell you something about the life of the late
                        <persName>Sir Richard Wells Bart.</persName> he took over <persName>the
                        Grange</persName> in 1919. He put up for parliament in 1922 and was elected.
                    The year he was elected twins was born <persName>Sarah</persName> and
                        <persName>Oliver</persName> who lives at <persName>Ickwell
                    Grange</persName>; near <placeName ref="#pl:biggleswade"
                        >Biggleswade</placeName>. I do not know anything about
                        <persName>Sarah</persName> at the time of writing. <persName>Richard
                        Wells</persName> was knighted in 1938 and he was made a Baron in 1944. He
                    had 7 sons and two daughters. He lost 3 sons in action in the 1939/45 war which
                    was a great shock to the whole village. The eldest son
                        <persName>Charles</persName> is in <placeName ref="#pl:canada"
                        >Canada</placeName> and has 2 sons. The 3 sons of the late <persName>Sir
                        Richard Wells Bart.</persName> are added to the names on the 1914/18 War
                    Memorial in the village. He would kindly consent for the village to have the use
                    of the Grange when we had a Fete as I myself was the Organiser on several
                    occasions. At one Fete we sent over £200 to the <placeName ref="#pl:bedford"
                        >Bedford</placeName> Hospital and also round about the same amount to the
                    Red Cross and I can tell you that all in the village used to help on these
                    occasions and made a grand success to help others <pb n="11"/> in need. There
                    was always whist drives etc. going on in the village life. We had a Memorial
                    Fund which was intended to get a Village Hall but after a time there did not
                    seem to be much interest taken in the Village Hall so at a Meeting it was agreed
                    to give £200 to the Church, £100 to <placeName ref="#pl:radwell-chapel"
                        >Radwell Chapel</placeName> and £50 to the Sports Club, and the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell-bus-shelter">Bus Shelter</placeName> erected at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> came out of that
                    fund.</p>
                <p part="N">The late <persName>Mr. E. Rust</persName> was Keeper for the late
                        <persName>Sir Richard Wells Bart.</persName> until his death,
                        <persName>Arthur Odell</persName> was his chauffeur for 40 years.
                        <persName>Lady Wells</persName> used to take an active part in the welfare
                    of the village. She was President of the W.I. for many years. <persName>Lady
                        Wells</persName> was the daughter of the late <persName>C. J.
                        Maltby</persName> who lived then where <persName>General Moore</persName>
                    lives today 1965. <persName>Sir Richard Wells Bart.</persName> was a keen
                    sportsman and liked to go shooting. He had shooting rights in several villages
                    and used to engage beaters on these occasions.</p>
                <p part="N"> The <persName>Ashpole</persName> family was born at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> there was 5 sons and 2
                    daughters, I cannot give all their records, <persName>William</persName> was
                    Shepherd for the Squire, <persName>Jack</persName> was horsekeeper and then in
                    the past years he worked on the Council at Rushden. <persName>Barnty</persName>
                    was Coachman for the Squire for sometime. <persName>Tom</persName> he worked in
                    London he has a son there now, as far as I know <persName>Miss Kate
                        Ashpole</persName> married <persName>Mr. A. Pack</persName>. Mr. and Mrs.
                    Ashpole the mother and father of the above moved into the house up the
                        <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName> Road when it was
                    built. I have been told that when it was being built they left off for a week or
                    two, there was a magpie built a nest there and it was then called <placeName
                        ref="#pl:magpie-hall">Magpie Hall</placeName>. After the
                        <persName>Ashpoles</persName> had passed on the house was taken over by
                        <persName>Mr. Pack</persName> and his wife and it had always been in the
                        <persName>Ashpole</persName> family since it was built and now
                        <persName>Mrs. Pack</persName> has passed on. She was the last of the
                    Ashpoles family and now the house is occupied by the daughter of <persName>Jack
                        Ashpole</persName> who married <persName>Fred Franklin</persName> so the
                    house still remains in the <persName>Ashpole</persName> family. I cannot go any
                    further about this house now.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a family of the <persName>Whitneys</persName>, the Mother was
                        <persName>Mary</persName> and the Father named <persName>George</persName>,
                    he was known in the village as <persName>Doudy</persName>. They had a large
                    family and according to the names it ran, <persName>Jack</persName>,
                        <persName>Saul</persName>, <persName>Faith</persName>,
                        <persName>Tin</persName>, <persName>Toto</persName>,
                        <persName>Peter</persName>, <persName>Norah</persName>,
                        <persName>Mark</persName> and <persName>Leonard</persName>, the baby
                        <persName>Doudy</persName> was a cripple for many years and used to go up to
                    town lot with two sticks. They lived in the house opposite the Suh for many
                    years, which is now pulled down. <persName>Mr. John Betts</persName> who I shall
                    be writing about later on, he worked for the Squire and used to clean the shoes
                    and was Handyman, he used to <pb n="12"/> bring a pint of beer each evening and
                    hand through the window for <persName>Doudy</persName>'s supper. I know this is
                    correct as I seen him on many occasions. Each evening he would bring the mail
                    bag to catch the post which left at 6.0 o'clock and then it was taken from
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> by a one armed man, the name
                    was <persName>Line</persName>, and he used to ride a 3 wheel tricycle. He would
                    bring the mail in the morning to <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> and then go on to <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham"
                        >Pavenham</placeName> and then in the evening he would leave <placeName
                        ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName> to arrive about 5.50 collect
                    Felmersham and then on to <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName>. The mail would go by train to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> and in the morning a man with a
                    horse and trap would meet the 0.30 at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> for the mail for <persName>Sharnbrook</persName>,
                        <persName>Harrold</persName> and all the villages round to be delivered by
                    the postman in the various villages. It was a hard day work in those days
                        <persName>Joe Bayes</persName> of <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> was the man who used to fetch the mail and after
                    that a man named <persName>Ridey</persName> took the job on. I can go no farther
                    on this problem.</p>
                <p part="N">Now I am going to write about the <persName>Betts</persName> family
                    which I will outline to you as near as I can. <persName>Mr. Thomas
                        Betts</persName> he used to live up the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:pavenham-road">Pavenham Road</placeName> in the end house next
                    to where the new bungalow is <persName>Mr. H. J. Cook's</persName> and son's
                    own, and the house I am referring to is owned by them today 1965.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr. Thomas Betts</persName> was Gamekeeper for the Squire for
                    many years. I knew him and his wife quite well, he had two sons one named
                        <persName>Arthur</persName> and the other <persName>Johnnie</persName>, the
                    daughters all I know was the one that married <persName>Sid Sumlin</persName>
                    in, the Father of <persName>Sam Sumlin</persName> who lives at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> today, and worked for
                        <persName>Mr. J. Hensman</persName>, <persName>Mr. Arthur Betts</persName>
                    lived at <persName>Carlton</persName> and was a Chimney Sweep and used to sweep
                    the chimney in all the big houses, he had a pony and cart to take his tackle
                    about until later years and then he used to run and walk and do the jobs,
                        <persName>Fred Betts</persName> and <persName>Arthur's son</persName> who
                    was Bakers etc, for many years, he had two children, <persName>Alwin</persName>
                    and <persName>Edna</persName> and when <persName>Alwin</persName> came back from
                    the 1939/45 war he he helped his father in the business and now he carry on the
                    business but is greatly extended it and has made alterations and is now a busy
                    concern. <persName>John Betts</persName> who married <persName>Miss
                        Howe</persName>, the daughter of <persName>Charlie Howe</persName>, who at
                    the time I think worked for the Squire, he was killed in the 1914/18 war on
                    September 24th, 1917, he took over the Secretary of the Free Gardeners Friendly,
                    known as Water Lily Lodge, also he dealt with National Health when they came
                    into force and then after he was killed his wife was allowed to carry on the
                    good work, <persName>Mrs. E. Betts</persName> lived in the same house all the
                    remainder of her life. According to what I can gather <persName>Charles
                        Howe</persName> at one time lived at <placeName ref="#pl:awkfall-farm"
                        >Hawkfall Farm</placeName>, now in the hands of <persName>H. J. Cook &amp;
                        Sons</persName>, he then came to live in the house owned by the late John
                    Betts' widow, where today <persName>Mr. W. Odell</persName> lives. <persName>Mr.
                        Charles Howe</persName> was one of the horsekeepers employed by the Squire
                        <pb n="13"/> he had 7 daughters and one son who daughter lives at the
                    council house, <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>* She
                    married <persName>Lesley Payne</persName>, they have two sons. <persName>Mrs.
                        Payne</persName> is caretaker at the school and also at the church in
                    1965.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr. George Howe, the father of Mrs. Payne who lived in the house which
                    belonged to the old Blacksmith shop which is now pulled down was between and was
                    situated on the ground next to <persName>Mr. Alwin Betts</persName> garage. The
                    Blacksmith was the name of <persName>Gamble</persName> he had a Blacksmith shop
                    at <persName>Milton Ernest</persName>, he used to come to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> 3 times a week, Mondays,
                    Wednesdays and Fridays to shoe the horses and do other repairs to the implements
                    used on the farm. He used to come after dinner on these days and would stay
                    until 9.0 o'clock in the evening. He drove a pony and cart. After his retirement
                        <persName>Mr. Charlie Clark</persName> who married Mr. Gamble's daughter
                    carried the work on and also the shop at <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest"
                        >Milton Ernest</placeName> and that is how the work went on in the village
                    in those days. <persName>Mr, G, Howe</persName> had the use of the house for
                    helping <persName>Mr. Gamble</persName> in the Blacksmith shop in the evenings.
                    It was a regular thing for Mr, Gamble to go across to the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sun-inn">Sun Inn</placeName> to have his bread and cheese and a
                    pint. He would always bring the crust of the bread for his pony. When Mr. Gamble
                    had shoed the horses which belong to the Squire he would let theu go home on
                    their own. There was no motor traffic about to knock them down those days and
                    that*s how the life in the village v/ent on,</p>
                <p part="N">There was in the village in those days <persName>Mr. Pool</persName>,
                        <persName>Mr. Brooks</persName>, <persName>Mr. J. Thomas</persName>,
                        <persName>Mr. Flemings</persName>, <persName>Mr, C. Robinson</persName> and
                        <persName>Mr. C, Cook</persName> up the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:hardwick-farm">Hardwick Farm</placeName>. Of course there was a
                    man known Mortain who farms up the <placeName ref="#pl:hardwick-farm"
                        >Hardwick Farm</placeName> before Mr. C, Cook took over. There was also Mr.
                    H. H, Green The Squire when Mr, Flemings senior died. His son took over the farm
                    Hugh Fleming and lived there with his mother and others in the family until it
                    was sold and was taken over by Mr. J, D, Hensman when the sale of the
                    Alexander's Estate who lived at the Bury Pavenham in those days. The farm where
                    Mr. Brooks farmed was sold the same time and was bought by the late Benjiman
                    Cook, the father of Mr, H, J, Cook who farms there today, accompanied by his two
                    sons Peter and David but have added a lot more to the farm since Mr, B. Cook
                    took it over from Mr, Brook. Mr, Brooks moved to Will ing ton and Mr. Hugh
                    Fleming moved to Hyde Farm at Olney, after the sale I myself drove Mr, Hugh
                    Fleming's sheep when he moved to Olney by road what a lot of changes have taken
                    place in the village since'those days,</p>
                <p part="N">Mr, Arthur James Cooper born on 11th June, 1880, he was married January
                    10th at Milton Ernest, He worked for Mr, Cook during the <pb n="14"/> First War
                    in 1914, he then lived at Dropshort, he worked on the Council for 20 years, he
                    rode his bicycle to Rushden which is about 14 miles a day. He left there and
                    worked for Arthur Saunders until he retired at the age of 73. He was a very
                    active gardener and won many prizes at flower shows. He kept his allotment on in
                    the Allotments at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> until it
                    came too much for him to do. He has lived in the house where he lives today for
                    approximately 45 years. The house is owned by Mr. Hensman, he has watched many a
                    cricket match. He had his allotment for 50 years. They have 1 boy and 3 girls
                    and 12 grandchildren. Mrs. A, Cooper was, born at Wootton in 1883, Mr, and Mrs.
                    Cooper attended Radwel 1^ot"40 years, Mrs. Cooper is the only member alive which
                    started the U.I. it was about 44 years ago. Lady Y/ells was the first President
                    and the Meeting Was held up the Grange for a good many years. Mrs, Cooper was
                    care- taker at the school for 14 years, Miss Lewie Hulatt was caretaker for many
                    years, she was the daughter of Jim Hulatt who lived where Mr, Morrison lives
                    today.</p>
                <p part="N">Miss Lewie Hulatt moved in the Row after her Father's death and stayed
                    there until she passed on. The rent those days was &lt; 1/- per week,</p>
                <p part="N">Mrs. Payne had 3 sons, William, Joseph, and Fred. Joseph was killed in
                    the 1914/18 war. They lived in the house at the far end of the Row, now occupied
                    by Tommy and Mrs. Morrison and family. The Paynes lived there for many years and
                    after the death of Mrs. Payne her son William Payne took the house over who
                    lived with his mother. William Payne known to everyone in the village as Tobey.
                    He was never married and has lived on his own since his mother died* He has now
                    moved into the house where his brother Fred lived and he is moved to where old
                    Ted Rust used to live.years ago. Inkey Ted as I have referred to in some of my
                    wr i t i ng.</p>
                <p part="N">William Payne has been connected with the Church for many years, the
                    Clerk and has been for over 40 years and now in 1965 is still going strong and
                    he is very much appreciated with those connected with the village and I would
                    like to add that I have known him all my life and he has been a good living man
                    always, ready to give a helping hand where it is needed. He has had various jobs
                    in his lifetime and what I would describe as being a very busy man all his life.
                    He has lived in <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> all
                    his life and he has served with a good many Vicars and others connected with the
                    Church •</p>
                <pb n="15"/>
                <p part="N">Fred Payne married the second daughter of the late William Rust, known
                    in the village as David Rustand who lived for many years in the house opposite
                    the <placeName ref="#pl:sun-inn">Sun Inn</placeName> on the corner going to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName>. He was the son of Mr•
                    Ted Rust, Inkey Ted. That house has been pulled down and the ground is in the
                    hands of David Rust's grandaughter the daughter of Charles Everest which I have
                    wrote about. Mr. and Mrs. Fred Payne lived for many years in the house where
                    Toby Payne lives today 1965, They had a family of 3 , one son and two daughters.
                    They are all married, Kathleen, she married the son of Tom Lovell who is
                    landlord of the <placeName ref="#pl:sun-inn">Sun Inn</placeName>. He took
                    over after Mr. H. G. Lawson died. The other daughter married Mr. L. Podd, who
                    are now living at Clapham and is Landlord of the Star Inn. The son Fred Payne is
                    married and is wife comes from Manchester and at the present time he is living
                    in the house which belongs to H. J. Cook &amp; Sons. Mr. and Mrs. Sid Lovell
                    have one son who is married and lives in a house known as Baileys Villas at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr. Alfred Roberts brother to Nobey Roberts and also William Roberts,
                    they all lived at Felmersham. Alfred Roberts who waa Horsekeeper for the Squire
                    lived across the field next to Mr, and Mrs. A. Cooper, Mr. Roberts had two
                    daughters Edith was a teacher at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham-school"
                        >Felmersham School</placeName> in my boy days., she was married but died
                    early in life when <persName>Mr. Alfred Roberts</persName> died. His other
                    daughter <persName>Isabella</persName> who looked after him took over the house
                    and is there today 1965. <persName>Isabella</persName> was never married. They
                    have always been connected with the Church, they were all in, The Choir and
                    Alfred was also a Bell Ringer in those days, also was <persName>Fred
                        Thomas</persName>, <persName>William Ashpole</persName>, <persName>Jack
                        Ashpole</persName>, <persName>William White</persName> and <persName>Charlie
                        Everest</persName> and others.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Nobey Roberts</persName> who lived with his Mother
                        <persName>Sophy</persName> in the house where <persName>Mrs.
                        Corse</persName> and <persName>Mrs. Roberts</persName> live today 1965. He
                    was never married.he was a man who in those days could turn his hand to any job,
                    he was a good thatcher, and hedgelayer. He used to do a lot of his work
                    peacework in those days, he would lay a hedge for about 10/- a chain. The last
                    job he done for me he layed a hedge in <placeName>Hilly Pyghtle</placeName> at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>, that was a good many
                    year ago.</p>
                <p part="N">It was very interesting in thosedays to watch them do their jobs and how
                    skilled they were in doing it. There were as there is today ploughing matches
                    but in those days that would be done by a pair of horses and what a skill it
                    was, the horses knew as much about the job they were about to do as the men. I
                    have seen in my time the ploughman hang his lines on the hames and go down the
                    field and set a rig by just speaking to the horses and it would be as straight
                    if not straighter that the tractor do today. They <pb n="16"/> used to take a
                    great interest in their work for a very small pay.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a man who lived at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName>, the name <persName>William White</persName> and he
                    was Cowman for the late <persName>Flemings</persName> who farmed Manor |Parm now
                    occupied by <persName>Mr. J. Hensman</persName> after <persName>Mr.
                        Fleming</persName>s death he was taken on by Hugh Flemings and in the winter
                    months he would go up in Hulatts Barn to thrash beans out and then would feed
                    the straw and kavins to the sheep in the yard and sometimes he would be in the
                    sheep pen cleaning the swede to feed to the sheep. I myself worked for
                        <persName>Mr. Hugh Fleming</persName> at this time as second milkman
                        <persName>Mr. Fleming</persName> would say I know if White is there as he
                    was always smoking his old clay pipe. He lived in the Row at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> and paid 1/- per week rent.
                    He had one daughter named <persName>Polly</persName> and she married a
                        <persName>Brown</persName> from <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton
                        Ernest</placeName>, he was killed in the 1914/18 War. They had several
                    children, after that she re-married a man name of <persName>Jim
                        Gardener</persName> who died some years ago. <persName>Mrs.
                        Gardener</persName> is now living with her daughter and son-in-law Mr. and
                    Mrs. George Millward in the council houses at Radwell. She is relation to the
                    Gadsbys who used to live at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> in those days. Mr. White was a very small man he was
                    head ringer at the Church and used to chime the bell for Morning and Evening
                    Service* He liked a game of skittles and he was good at that. <persName>Mr. J.
                        Bamford</persName> kept the <placeName ref="#pl:plough-inn">Plough
                        Inn</placeName>. At Christmas time the ringers in those days would go round
                    for their Xmas Boxes, they would get a barrel of beer. The Carrier would bring
                    from Newland and Nashes from <placeName ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName>
                    you could get a 7 gallons barrel for 7/6d. and I/- off the barrel when it was
                    returned and when they would assemble to celebrate they would always ring the
                    old year out and the new one in and this is how the life went on in the village.
                    It was a happy life and you would make your own amusements in the village on
                    these special occasions.</p>
                <p part="N">There is a great history about the <persName>Robinson</persName> and the
                        <persName>Mitchell</persName> family. There was a man named
                        <persName>Mitchell</persName> who used to be Landlord of the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:plough-inn">Plough Inn</placeName> and according to what I can
                    gather there was also a <persName>Mitchell</persName> who Landlord of the
                        <placeName ref="#pl:six-ringers-inn">Six Ringers</placeName> at about
                    this time. The Mitchell's according to what I can gather worked the Farm known
                    as Brook Farm. Mr. Charles Robinson married the daughter of Mr. Mitchell who
                    kept the <placeName ref="#pl:plough-inn">Plough Inn</placeName> and after
                    their marriage Mr. Charlei Robinson took over the farm and is in the Robinson
                    family today. Mr. Charles Robinson is the son of George Robinson who one time
                    lived at <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton Ernest</placeName> and his
                    brother Tom, who at this time lived at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName>, and they both worked for Mr. Hugh Flemings but
                    these two brothers could never get on with each other, I know this to be true
                    because I knew both of them. There is one time I quite remember Mr. Hugh
                    Flemings dare not put them to work together if they were loading mangolds in the
                    fields, one would try to throw one over the cart to hit the other and then the
                    storm would start, <pb n="17"/> and that's how the happy lads got on together, I
                    think I am right Mr. Fleming had to give George the sack and all was O.K. then
                    with his brother Tom.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr. Charles Robinson farmed there until he retired, he had 3 sons,
                    Edward, Charles and Harry. Edward he farmed at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> until he retired. Charles he took to the butchering
                    line and worked at Rushden. Then he took over Butch Barker's business as far as
                    I am aware and then afterwards he made a big business in the High Street,
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>,also he farmed
                    land at <placeName ref="#pl:souldrop">Souldrop</placeName> and <placeName
                        ref="#pl:colworth">Colworth</placeName>. He carried on his business until
                    his retirement about 2 years ago and now as far as I know he lives at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>. He had two sons, I do not
                    know where the sons are today. He was a man who was always ready to help anyone
                    in need, and help them over a stile if he could do so. I have sold him pigs and
                    calves many a time, he would be fair in his dealing, he was liked and respected
                    in every way. I myself cannot speak too high of him as I have been associated
                    with him all my life. I worked for his father when I was a boy, I had 6d. a
                    day,before I left school as I used to work sheep keeping for him. When I left
                    school at 13 I had 6/- per week, but I must say I had many a meal there. Mrs*
                    Robinson would always see that I had hot tea and something to eat she was a very
                    good lady, and I am sure Charles Robinson her husband was one of the best you
                    could wish to meet.</p>
                <p part="N">Harry was the youngest of the three sons, he was farming at the time of
                    his father's retirement at Wilses Farm at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> where Mrs. Hitchin farms today 1965. Harry taken
                    over the farm of his father and carried on a milk round at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> until later on when his
                    daughter Jean got married and today they have a milking herd, and their milk
                    goes away each morning. Mr, and Mrs. H. Robinson has two children a son and
                    daughter, both married, Jean, Mr. and Mrs. Elliott has two sons and do contract
                    work etc. Harry the son helps his father on the farm. They have a family of two.
                    They live at <placeName ref="#pl:dropshort">Dropshort</placeName>. The
                    Robinson family have several generations they can look back on and at this point
                    I wish them all luck and prosperity as myself I been associated with them all my
                    life, I had the pleasure of meeting their uncles Frank, Robert Harry, William.
                    They used to come to the farm to visit their brother. The time I was there as a
                    boy Mr. Joe Lovell married Mr. C. Robinson's sister who was a signalman at
                    Souldrop for many years and her brother Charles used to call at Souldrop on his
                    way back from Rushden after delivering his eggs, butter etc. I used to go with
                    him when his wife were unable to go to look after the pony which was named Bob,
                    Mr. Robinson would buy me 2d. whisky and a pork pie at The Wagon &amp; Horses on
                    our way home. We would <pb n="18"/> arrive home about 4,0 o'clock. On one
                    occasion when Mrs. Robinson and a man known in the village as Lay Truitt was
                    going to Rushden the pony shied and ran on the grass and tipped the trap over.
                    Mrs. Robinson the grandmother of Harry Robinson of Dropshort, was thrown out and
                    injured. There was a lot of history about the Robinson family. I have wrote all
                    the main things I know.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr. C* Robinson was a good trainer of dogs and also of break- ing in his
                    horses and I think the same applies to all the family in the olden days. They
                    are still going strong and carrying on the good work. Harry Robinson junior has
                    land he farms at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> in 1965, he
                    has taken the land off his uncle Ted at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> now retired.</p>
                <p part="N">Tom Robinson was brother to George Robinson who I have wrote about, he
                    worked for Mr. Flemings at <placeName ref="#pl:manor-farm">Manor
                        Farm</placeName> and he lived in the cottages now occupied by Mrs. Morris
                    for a good many years. The cottages used to go with the farm and they do today
                    1965. Mr* and Mrs. Robinson, Mrs. Robinson's was named Eliza, she was a very
                    active woman and would walk miles. She kept bees and would sell her honey, I
                    seen her many a time when the bees set off, follow them rattling an old tin to
                    get the bees to swarm and then she would go and collect them. On one occasion
                    she took her husband's dinner, this used to be a regular practice it did not
                    suit him so he smashed the plates up, so she made no more to do collected the
                    plates up and next day she put them in his gravy pudding, set his dinner down
                    and tore back up <placeName>Stipens Hill</placeName> that is up the
                        <placeName>Carlton Road</placeName> and when Tom cut his pudding there was
                    the bit of broken plates inside. You may think this is a strange story but it
                    was true how things went on, when Tom went homsat night I cannot say. They had
                    two sons one was named Harry and the other named Tom, Harry took over the Plough
                    after MitchelIs left it as far as I know, he kept a sweet shop and also cows
                    which used to be milked in the old Plough Yard. I seen them milk them many a
                    time. Harry Robinson used to employ a man named Harry Hulatt, we used to call
                    uppercut to keep them on the road side, Ernest Home who now lives at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> and Fred Surridge known as
                    Baggy who now lives at Odell were employed by him as boys at different times. He
                    used to have two small bits of grass one was where Baileys Villas are built
                    today, and the other bit was on the Odell Road, known as 3 Cornered Bit. The
                    Cows were put in there for the night and out on the road side in the morning.
                    The road side needed no cutting those days. Old Nobey Roberts would say you
                    cannot get a bent to clean your pipe out with. Mr. and Mrs. H. Robinson went to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton Ernest</placeName> and took
                    over the <placeName ref="#pl:swan-inn">Swan Inn</placeName>, for a time then
                    they <pb n="19"/> moved up the Brickyard at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> and carried on a milk round, Mr. H. Robinson was
                    kicked by a cow and he died. They had two daughters, May and Kathleen who used
                    to help with the milk round they had at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName>* Mr. Robinson used to employ several different old
                    men to keep his cows on the road side when he moved to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> Brickyard. The daughters are
                    now living together at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                    >Sharnbrook</placeName>, Tom Robinson married and lived at Felmersham and used
                    to make shoes for some Rushden firm, he lived in the house how occupied by Mr.
                    C. Everest's daughter and son-in-law he used to make shoes in the barn on the
                    side of the house. Mr. Fred Payne used to help work for him for a time, they had
                    rather a large family but I cannot give further details. Mr. Robinson moved to
                    Kettering from <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> they
                    were related to Mr. Alfred Roberts. The last I heard about them their son Fred
                    who went to school with me was still living at Kettering. That is as far as I
                    can go with this family.</p>
                <p part="N">The house where Tom Robinson used to live have been all done up and a
                    new bit added where he used to have his workshop and has also made practically a
                    new home. It all points out to what can be done to make things more comfortable
                    to live in and I would - at this point like to congratulate them both in the
                    good work done on this cottage.</p>
                <p part="N">Fred Payne he worked for the Squire and he had the misfortune to be
                    kicked with one of the Squire's horses in the face, he worked on the County
                    Council for many years, he drove a steam roller for many years until he retired
                    on pension,in his retirement he liked to do gardening, to help him along in his
                    retirement. He has lived all his life in <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName>, he is about 76. He has been a good skittle and also
                    a good dart player in his time. </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>Thomas. Jack, Sam and Ted.</head>
                <p part="N">Sam Thomas was a wheelwright and Carpenter, he carried on his business
                    which is now occupied by Mr. Greenaway, he is in the fishing float manufacture.
                    This cottage was built in 1883, Mr. A. Pacey carried on the business as a
                    Wheelwright etc. for many years, he had 2 children, his son Tom was in the
                    1914/18 war and lost a leg, his daughter Sybil she played the organ at the
                    Church. For many years she was also a teacher for a time at the school, Mr.
                    Pacey was the Peoples Warden for many years, this family took an active part in
                    the Church,</p>
                <p part="N">Edward Thomas was a Stonemason, he used to live at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> in the house now occupied by Mr.
                    and Mrs. Horsford in the <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell <pb n="20"/>
                        Lane</placeName>, he had 3 children, 2 sons and a daughter. The son George
                    Thomas was a Carpenter and lived at Rushden for many years• The daughter was
                    named Bertha and kept house for her Father for many years. She moved to the end
                    house in the Row for many years. Ted Thomas, as he was known in those days used
                    to work for Pacey at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>
                    and other builders. He was a very good stonemason and worked on the bridges,
                    churches and anywhere where there was stone work to be carried out. Fred Thomas
                    married George Willis daughter, and lived with them at Willis' farm now occupied
                    by Mrs. Hitchin.</p>
                <p part="N">Jack Thomas was a Farmer, Baker and Sho#pkeeper, he also kept the Post
                    Office, he had the Shop and Bake house now occupied by Mr* Alwin Betts, he used
                    to have two farms, one known as Parsons Barn Farm, now in possession of Mr,
                    Ibbott and also Willis Farm now in possession of Mrs* Hitchin. He farmed these
                    two farms until he moved to <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> to take over Rolstons Farm now in occupation of Mr.
                    Ibbott, when he moved to <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> he was a wealthy man but I am sorry to say that this
                    was his downfall, he returned to Felmersham and for a time lived again at the
                    shop. He spent his last days in the house now occupied by Mr. and Mrs. G.
                    Hulatt. He was a very good farmer, and employed a lot of men, Jack Ashpole at
                    one time was a horsekeeper, also John Barker of <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName>, he used to look after the horses down Parsons 3arn.
                    The reason it was named Parsons Barn, it was the living of the Parson at
                    Felmersham and the rent had to be paid to the Parson and then the farm was sold,
                    after Jack Thomas left the farm. It was farmed by Mr* W* Brook who then had the
                    farm where H. J, Cook &amp; Sons farm today 1965.</p>
                <p part="N">After Mr* Jack Thomas moved to <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> the shop was taken over by Mr* Robert Whitworth also
                    the Bake house and Post Office. He carried on the business for many years, he
                    had one son and several daughters. The son*George is a painter and decorater and
                    lives at <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName>, also two of the
                    daughters Gladys, Hilda, Mr* R. Whitworth lived at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> for a good many years until he died
                    at the age 90. He was the son of Joseph Whitworth who was a horsekeeper for many
                    years for the late Mr. Flemings at <placeName ref="#pl:manor-farm">Manor
                        Farm</placeName> now occupied by Mr, J« Hensman. Robert Whitworth married
                    the daughter of Joseph Whitworth. The late Mr* Herbert Scrivener married another
                    daughter and they lived in the house now occupied by Mr* and Mrs, John Bamford.
                    They had one son Bert, and as far as I know he lives at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> today 1965.</p>
                <p part="N">There was <persName>Brother Whitworth</persName> who lived in the
                    cottage in <pb n="21"/>
                    <persName>Hardwick Close</persName> which is now fell down, his name was
                        <persName>Jim V/h it worth</persName> and he worked for the late
                        <persName>Mr. Flemings</persName> and fed the cattle down <persName>Red
                        Barn</persName> in the winter. I met him and talk with him on many-
                    occasions. I myself worked for the late <persName>Mr, Flemings</persName> for.
                    several years also my brother <persName>Fred</persName>, who was killed in 1917,
                    he was the youngest in our family, he was born on Xmas day.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>William Lathbridge</persName> was Vicar when I was a boy and
                    he had several daughters who used to teach us at Sunday School as there were
                    several classes in those days. The one that teached ihy class was named
                        <persName>Jenny</persName> and she married the Squire's son <persName>Robin
                        Green</persName>, they were both interned in <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> Churchyard, also the son of
                    the Vicar.</p>
                <p part="N">Then came <persName>Bruce Cuming</persName> Vicar 1903, he was never
                    married, but he did a lot for the Church and the Welfare of the village. He also
                    had a brother who lived with him which was named Don. Their servant at this time
                    was a <persName>Miss Parrish</persName> who married <persName>Mr. Herbert
                        Hulatt</persName> who lives at <persName>Harrold</persName> today 1965. She
                    now lives with her brothers as she lost her husband several year ago. </p>
                <p part="N">Bruce Cumming Vicar, used to give a tea each year to all in the Parish,
                    he would have the school children first and then one for middle age and then he
                    would finish up with all the old ones and we used to look forward to it.
                        <persName>Mr. Robert Whitworth</persName> used to provide the tea when the
                    1914-18 war was on, he sent a food parcel to everyone in the Forces from the
                    village, I had mine the time I was in France. He did a good lot for the village
                    in general. There are two names outstanding in my mind <persName>Mrs.
                        Drage</persName> and <persName>Mrs. Makeham</persName>. Mrs. Makeham's son
                    lives at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> 1965.</p>
                <p part="N">Then in 1917 we had <persName>Lawrence Rowden Levett</persName>. He was
                    a very good man to the Parish and he took an active part in sport he would play
                    at football and he would take part in anything that was going on. I had to call
                    on him on one occasion when we had a cricket supper held at the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:plough-inn">Plough Inn</placeName>, as <persName>Sir Richard
                        Wells</persName> could not come to present the medals and he came and
                    obliged. When our first child was born he went to
                        <placeName>Knotting</placeName> to fetch the nurse who was then Nurse
                    Doughty at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>. She had
                    another case at Knotting and one at Souldrop and Nurse Doughty walked unless you
                    could find transport for her in those days, This was on a Sunday morning, and he
                    was 15 minutes late in taking the Service and on the Evening Service he
                    announced we had a baby daughter. He would read his text from the bible, close
                    hia <pb n="22"/> Bible and off he go and preach his sermon and you would be out
                    by 7.0 o'clock. He was well liked in the village and did good work to keep the
                    village active.</p>
                <p part="N">We have now the <persName>Rev. Sidebottom</persName> who looks after the
                    Parish of <placeName ref="#pl:bletsoe">Bletsoe</placeName> and <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>, he is taking an active part
                    to improve the life of the village and we hope in due course the new vicarage
                    will be built so he will be able to come and live among us and carry on the good
                    work which I sure he is out to do. He has a lot on his hands in the two villages
                    and with the help of both villages I hope he will make his job worth while. At
                    the time of writing <persName>Mr, J. Hensman</persName> is the Vicar's warden
                    and <persName>Mr, L. J. Church</persName> is the People's warden, <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham-church">Felmersham Church</placeName> is a fine
                    Church and the finest village church in the country and the people who live in
                    the village are proud to have such a fine church.</p>
                <p part="N">I have in my life in my young days attended the Church as we used to
                    march over from the School from Sunday School to take part in the service. There
                    was a good choir in those days and they used to take an active part in the
                    singing* There was a large attendance in those days especially in the evening.
                    The daughter of <persName>Leathbridges</persName> was a great singer. The
                        <persName>Linnetts</persName> of <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham"
                        >Pavenham</placeName> would ' attend Church when they could do so, and so
                    the life went on in the village 60 year ago.</p>
                <p part="N">The <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> School in
                    1845 it was a church school under the authority of the Vicar and church wardens.
                    The management is now in the hands of the County Council. The teacher at the
                    present day is Head Mistress, Miss Pacey who comes from <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>. In the olden days there was
                    Head Master Mr. Wilkenson and he lived in the.house which joined the school and
                    is now where the cooking and children's meals are prepared. It used to be known
                    as the Village Room where meetings could be held without interferring with the
                    School but in the last few years things have changed and now they are held in
                    the school.</p>
                <p part="N">When I went to school the little ones used to go after they turned 3.
                    There was them days the son of the old school master he was a very short man and
                    he did not have what you would call in these days good control of the boys, they
                    more or less used to control the school master and if the boys got out of hand
                    he would call in the Vicar, or the Squire. Then if one of the boys had done
                    wrong he would march the infants out to take the boy in for his hiding. I
                    remember once he had got a boy, Arthur Rust in for a whacking he picked up a
                    form and droped on the school master's toes and he was hopping about for 6
                    weeks. On another occasion he had got a boy named Fred Oadsby, this boy was my
                    own mate. The school <pb n="23"/>Master got him between his knee and started
                    tanning his backside when <persName>Fred Gadsby</persName> .stuck his teeth in
                    the School Master's backside. We could hear him shouting let loose in the
                    school, and that's how things went on in those days. My own brother Jack has
                    taken the cane away and broke it in two and put it on the fire. So the boys are
                    no worse in 1965 than they was in 1900. Of course they have stricter control of
                    the school today. It was no strange thing to see the mother come down to school
                    to have it out with the School Master, but I would like to tell you he went a
                    bit far at times with his punishment and thats what used to cause the
                    trouble.</p>
                <p part="N">Most of our family left <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> School and went to Sharn- brook School,
                        <persName>Mr. Colson</persName> was School Master there and he had better
                    control of the children. The reason my brother Frank, was ordered to stay in
                    school but he had been told he was to take the Donkey and cart to meet my Father
                    down Parsons Barn, so he ran out' of school and the School Master and Miss
                    Roberts after him and he was going through the stile against the house or
                    bungalow now known as <persName>Trinity Close</persName> and there he got clear.
                    Well next morning my Mother took him down to the School and the School Master
                    said he would put him back two standards. So my Mother took him home and after
                    that we all went to <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>
                    School. When my Mother was coming out of the school the Squire was coming up the
                    hill by the school. He used to call my Mother, Betsy, and then she told him what
                    had happened and she was sending us to <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> School. I was at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> School with the brother and sister of the Head
                    School Mistress which is now at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> School 1965. We used to go across the Meadows to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> when the floods
                    was not out. If the floods were on the rise Mr. Colson would send us out
                    earlier, so we could get over on the planks as it soon came over in those days,
                    it was rather a rough life in those days.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a lot went to <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName> School, after we started to go there were also a lot
                    come from Souldrop to the School. A man named Ernest Barns and also Rool Newell
                    were teachers there in my days at School. Mr. Prince Evans was School Master at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> School when.there
                    was 100 children attended. My wife was there at the time and they had half a day
                    holidays. Then Mr, Evans left Felmersham and went to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> School. There were various
                    other teachers, Miss Farren, Mrs, Killen was before she married, Miss Brooks,
                    her father farmed where Mr. H. J. Cook and Sons farm today before they moved to
                    Willington. Now today I have 4 grand- children attend today. I hope this will be
                    of interest to those who care to read. This is true as far as I can explain to
                    you.</p>
                <p part="N">Now I would like to say a little about the sport carried on in <pb
                        n="24"/> the village in my boy days and also since about 1900 as far as I
                    can. There was always a good cricket team in the village, they won several cups
                    at cricket and football. <persName>Mr, A, Odell</persName> was captain for
                    several years. Sir Richard Wells was President for a good many years.
                        <persName>Mr. Hugh Fleming</persName> took a very great interest in the
                    cricket team. He played with <persName>Master H. Green</persName> and
                        <persName>Robin Green</persName> and others. They had a good team in those
                    days, it was a usual thing to play a married and single match on Whit Monday
                    each year. It were Robin Green's Team against Hugh Fleming's team, Robin Green's
                    team would be <persName>Nobey Roberts</persName>, <persName>Changey</persName>,
                        <persName>Alfred Roberts</persName>, <persName>Fred Thomas</persName> and
                    others. <persName>Master Harry Green</persName> would usually play with Robin
                    Green's team. Hugh Fleming's team would be the.single team and what a day that
                    was. Beer, bread and cheese would be provided up to the finish. The Squire would
                    umpire sometimes, I remember they appealed to the Squire. He said Not Out, but
                    if you do it again it will be. They used to finish the day up usual at the
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sun-inn">Sun Inn</placeName> kept then by the Hilton
                    family.</p>
                <p part="N">There was in those days a cricket pitch in the Mead on the Sharnbrook
                    side where the first eleven used to play. They were what we used to call in
                    those days The Toff Team and it was a good one.</p>
                <p part="N">The Cricket Team won the cups.</p>
                <p part="N">2nd Division in 1922.</p>
                <p part="N">2nd Division in 1929</p>
                <p part="N">2nd Division in 1937.</p>
                <p part="N">3rd Division in 1928.</p>
                <p part="N">South Sec. 1933.</p>
                <p part="N">They had a Football team and won the cup in 1925 and 26 Season. They
                    also played friendly games and we had a fairly good team in those days.
                        <persName>Mr. H. G. Lawson</persName> was captain and I was secretary. It
                    was then made a sports club as is at the present day and the team seem to give a
                    good account of themselves. It was in 1963 they won the division they were in
                    and are still going strong. They have played in the same field for years kindly
                    lent by the late Mr« Flemings and now by <persName>Mr. Tom Hensman</persName>.
                    There has been some good struggles in that old field. We played in the first
                    division but we were not good enough for such teams. I myself when we played at
                    Britannia works, their ground is at Kemps ton took 6 wickets for 6 runs and only
                    bowled 17 balls in this first division match. <persName>Mr, A. Odell</persName>
                    was captain at that time, we lost as they got a good score before I went on to
                    bowl. Mr. W. Hulatt was on the other end, <persName>Fred Purser</persName> and
                        <persName>Joe Hulatt</persName> was two of our best bowlers at that time.
                    Joe lives at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> and Fred
                    Purser at <pb n="25"/> Souldrop in 1965,</p>
                <p part="N">Hardwick Farm now occupied by Mr. and Mrs. Kerns ley they taken the farm
                    over from Mr, Tom Cook when he left to go to Warden Hill Farm, Everton, Tom
                    Cook's mother could be seen along the Carl ton Road keeping her son's cows in
                    her younger days she would drive her pony and trap to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName>. She would always go <placeName
                        ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName> Road way as she would call at
                    Gadsbys each Saturday to bring their groceries from <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> as there was no buses in those
                    days, Gadsbys lived in the last house on the right hand side going to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName>. <persName>Mrs. Cook</persName>
                    was a <persName>Partridge</persName> from <persName>Bletsoe</persName>.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a man named <persName ref="#ps:morton">Morton</persName>
                    who lived at <placeName ref="#pl:hardwick-farm">Hardwick Farm</placeName>
                    before Cook as far as I know, he used to carry on the farm. He had a son named
                        <persName ref="#ps:morton-albert">Albert</persName>, he married one of
                    the Howe daughters according to what I can gather which used to live at Hawkfull
                    Farm and they went to <placeName>Canada</placeName>. There was <persName
                        ref="#ps:morton-emma"/>Emma and <persName ref="#ps:morton-fanny"
                        >Fanny</persName>, two daughters. <persName ref="#ps:morton-fanny"
                        >Fanny</persName> married a man named <persName ref="#ps:cotton-josh"
                    />Josh Cotton and they are both alive and live in
                        <placeName>Nuneaton</placeName>. They lived up the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:hardwick-farm">Hardwick Farm</placeName> in the Boar War. It
                    was a serious blow to them as the pond was poisoned and they lost all their
                    horses and cattle. They then left the farm and went to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName> to be Carpenter on the Estate of
                    Alexandra. The old people in the village would remember them, I do myself quite
                    well. How I got this record was from the daughter <persName
                        ref="#ps:morton-fanny">Fanny</persName> which I have mentioned above, it
                    is as far as I now a true record.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a man named <persName ref="#ps:mason-fred">Fred
                        Mason</persName> he was what they would call in those days a Higler, he kept
                    pigs and done a bit of farming. He used to have the field up the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:pavenham-road">Pavenham Road</placeName> named <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bagwell">Bagwell</placeName>. He had the building which went
                    with the Fleming Farm against the <placeName ref="#pl:six-ringers">Six
                        Ringers</placeName> in the occupation of <persName ref="#ps:payne-w">Mr.
                        W. Payne</persName> before they started build- ing in <placeName
                        ref="#pl:marriotts-close">Marriotts Close</placeName>. <persName
                        ref="#ps:mason-fred">Mr. Mason</persName> was also a shoe mender and
                    made shoes. He had a horse and trap and he was a carrier and used to go to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> Wednesday and Saturdays.
                    He lived at the time in the house where <persName ref="#ps:marr">Mr. and
                        Mrs. Marr</persName> up <placeName ref="#pl:town-hot-lane">Town Hot
                        Lane</placeName>, There was also a carrier known as <persName
                        ref="#ps:payne-amos">Amos Payne</persName> he lived at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> at the time where <persName
                        ref="#ps:norman-jack">Mr. Jack Norman</persName> lives today. He only
                    went to <placeName ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> on Saturdays, He had
                    a son named <persName ref="#ps:payne-william">William</persName>, he went to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:canada">Canada</placeName> after his father died*
                    Then a bit later on <persName ref="#ps:bowyer-horace">Mr. Horace
                        Bowyer</persName> who lived at Dropshort started up carrying business. He
                    was the father of my wife, now <persName ref="#ps:turner-rose">Mrs* R,
                        Turner</persName>. They moved from <placeName ref="#pl:dropshort"
                        >Dropshort</placeName> down to take <placeName ref="#pl:swan-inn-radwell"
                        >Radwell Pub</placeName> over, but still carried on the carrying business
                    until he went to <placeName ref="#pl:hill-farm">Hill Farm</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> to be foreman for
                        <persName>Hipwell &amp;c Sons</persName>, and from there he left to take a
                    farm over at <placeName ref="#pl:bowness">Bowness</placeName> and there he
                    died at an early age.</p>
                <pb n="26"/>
                <p part="N">There was no buses to take you those days. The passengers used to get
                    out and walk up the hills to ease the old horse a bit. <persName
                        ref="#ps:bowyer-horace">Mr. Bowyer</persName> had a 4 wheel brake. I
                    remember going to <placeName ref="#pl:sandy">Sandy</placeName> Flower Show
                    with a load of women once. That was rather a big day for the old horse but we
                    managed it, there was <persName ref="#ps:gadsby-p">Mrs. P.
                    Gadsby</persName>, <persName ref="#ps:rust">Mrs, Rust</persName> and others.
                    I cannot remember went that day. I know it was a fine day, I was courting my
                    wife as is now at the time so it must have been nearly^O years ago.</p>
                <p part="N">If you wanted to go to <placeName ref="#pl:bedford"
                        >Bedford</placeName> you could catch a train at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> which they did in those days
                    but it was a good walk when you got out at <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook"
                        >Sharnbrook</placeName>, but now the buses take you nearly to your door,
                    what a change it is today than it was 60 to 80 years ago.</p>
                <p part="N">Now I would like to write a few lines about my own life in the last 74
                    years also a little about our family. I went to school until I was 13 and worked
                    for Mr. C. Robinson until I was in my 15, then I went on the Railway at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> as a lamp boy. I
                    was at <persName>Twywell</persName> on the <persName>Kettering</persName> and
                        <persName>Cambridge</persName> branch until I was 18 and then I was sacked
                    because I could not pass the Dr. to join the Railway Club, I came home and
                    worked for Mr, Hugh Flemings and then after then I worked in the woods at
                    Colworth, and then in 1914 I joined up on August 11th in the Army. I was the
                    first one from Felmersham to volunteer in 1914/18 war. I left England for France
                    in 1915. I was a Platoon Sergeant in France. I was in charge of 60 men and went
                    over the top several times. I was on the Somme Battle and various other
                    engagements. I was in London in charge it a time at Offord Road, Barnsley. I was
                    acting Sergeant Major when I was discharged in 1918. I was married on 19th
                    December 1919 and I lived in the same house for 45 years, this year. I have one
                    daughter and 3 sons and 8 grandchildren.</p>
                <p part="N">My father was Henry Turner and my mother's maiden name was Turner so
                    they did not change their names. They had 21 children they brought up 15, 6
                    girls and 9 boys. The other 6 died in child birth* My Father drove a pair of
                    donkeys at one time. He used to work on the Railway as a Platelayer, in his
                    later years he drove his donkeys and cart to work to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook-railway-station">Sharnbrook Station</placeName>. The
                    late Mr. Pacey of <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> made
                    him a new donkey cart and the late Mr. Fountain of <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> made him a new set of harness
                    for the donkey. The late Sir Richard Wells bought the donkey at my Father's
                    sale. My Father was 71 when he died on August 29th 1927. My Mother died on May
                    3rd 1925 and are interned in <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> Churchyard. I have my brother, ArJ;hur and my sister
                    Dora and also my brother Charles^Tll^^^oMr^Ba^passed on except my sister Ida who
                    lived at <placeName ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> she will be 80 this
                    year, so there is only two of us left out of our large family 1965.</p>
                <pb n="27"/>
                <p part="N">There was the Jeffreys family they live in the cottage known as the
                        <placeName ref="#pl:bridge-cottage">Bridge Cottage</placeName>, when it
                    was sold Mr, and Mrs. Frank Desborough bought it. Mr. Desborough kept the
                        <placeName ref="#pl:six-ringers-inn">Six Ringers</placeName> when Squire
                    Green was about and then at one time they lived in the bungalow where Mr, A.
                    Odell lives today and used to let boats out and provide tea. Mrs. Desborough had
                    a grandaughter named Betty, she married my second son John, they now live at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:rushden">Rushden</placeName>, they have a son and a
                    daughter, Linda and Robert.</p>
                <p part="N">In the two villages most of the houses had a pig sty in the garden and
                    they used to keep perhaps 2 pigs. Mr. Newell was Baker at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> and used to supply the
                    feeding stuff corn for the hens and so when the pigs were ready to be killed Mr.
                    Newell would take part of the pigs to cover the food stuff and that's how it
                    went on in the good old days in <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName>. Of course some would pay as they went along.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a man who used to live in the house known as Underwood Farm of
                    the name of G. Ward, he used to go and kill the pigs at the houses. There was
                    only several in the village who had a tub and scrat, so they used to borrow it
                    to dress the pig in. The copper would be got boiling and so on. This man G. Ward
                    always had beer on these occasions, then in the evening he would come and cut up
                    the pig the way you wanted it and then it was put in salt and aired and hung up
                    round the house, they were what the old folks would say good pictures and all
                    the offals used to be made into faggots and goodlard.</p>
                <p part="N">I remember once my Father Had a sow killed and that weighed over 20
                    score and that hung in the barn where Sam Lovell lives today 1965. That was cut
                    and come again. That is how things went on 70 years ago.</p>
                <p part="N">In the old day most of the farm had what they used to call Dove House
                    where the pigeons used to come and the farmers could get a few for dinner when
                    they wanted any. There was one in Marriotts Close not far from the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:six-ringers-inn">Six Ringers</placeName> which in those days
                    belonged to the <placeName ref="#pl:manor-farm">Manor Farm</placeName>, There
                    was a footpath went by the old Dove House and used to come out in Harvest Yard
                    where the bungalows are built known as Trinity Close and out against the Church,
                    There are various footpaths leading out of the village. There is one which goes
                    up to <placeName ref="#pl:hardwick-farm">Hardwick Farm</placeName> which used
                    to be used not many years ago. Bob Marsh used to go that way to attend Mr. J. O,
                    Hensman's sheep. There is one used to go over the stile where now Mr. J, Bamford
                    lives. There was also one which went in the gate on the left hand side coming to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> in Mr, Tom Hensman's
                    field across the <pb n="28"/> middle and out into <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bakers-lane">Bakers Lane</placeName> up the Lane and across the
                    field known as the Bents and then across to <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> over the Collich Lane and across the field known as
                    Knights Close on to Moor End Road over the Mill at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> and on to Thurleigh. The Rad-
                    well footpaths one go in where Mr. E. Robinson lives over the field and then on
                    down to Parsons Barn. There was one footpath come along <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bakers-lane">Bakers Lane</placeName> by Mr, H. Robinsons at
                    Dropshort across the road into Mr. L. J. Church's field and come out against the
                    Dutch Barns across <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName> Road up
                    to Hawksfull and on to Turvey.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>Post Office.</head>
                <p part="N">There was no Post Office at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> until Mrs Hulatt took it over for 5 months in 1918
                    and she is still at the Post Office,</p>
                <p part="N">At the time when there was no Post Office a man named Charlie White he
                    was gardener at the Vicarage, he used to go to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> Post Office to fetch the old
                    age pensions for those in the village. The Post Office was at the shop where Mr,
                    A. Betts is today. Before Mrs. Hulatt took over the Post Office I think it was
                    held by Mr. Robert Whitworth, all the mail at one time used to come to Sharn-
                    brook and then after that it came to <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham"
                        >Pavenham</placeName>. The Postman used to have to collect it at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName> and now today it comes direct to
                    Felmersham to be delivered by the various Post Ladies. What a change it has been
                    in the last 60 years and the same Post Mistress since Mrs. Hulatt took, over,
                    what a record to be sure. She must have seen a few changes,in her younger days
                    she was on various commit ties. She was on the Village Hall Committee when we
                    was trying to raise money to build a village hall and took an active part in the
                    life of the village. I have just been told that she is giving up the Post Office
                    in May 1965.</p>
                <p part="N">In the time that the late Mr. Fleming was farming at Manor Farm there
                    was rather a strange thing happened. There was some Gipsy called Smith, Jimmy
                    Smith and him and his wife and family used to travel the road and often camp on
                    Daisy Bank up the CarIton Road, they were often round the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> district and the village
                    people in those days knew them quite well. On one of their visits Mrs, Jimmy
                    Smith has a son born on Daisy Bank, Mr. Fleming took pity on them and let them
                    go down into Red Barn and he sent milk and food and blankets down to them each
                    morning. Someone had to go and take them their food and that went on until Mr.
                    and Mrs. Smith and family could take to the Road again. There was a man named
                    Jim Whitworth used to live in the cottage in Hardwick Close who worked for Mr.
                    Flemings, at this time his brother Joe Whitworth was his housekeeper, lived in
                    the house where Mr. S, Sum!in lives today 1965.</p>
                <pb n="29"/>
                <p part="N"> Gipsy Jimmy had a lot of children. There is one named Abergell and she
                    and Joe Smith fiave been together and they are known all over <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName>shire asv Joe and Annie, They are
                    well known in Felmersham and <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                    >Radwell</placeName>, they are known of two of the old fashion Romanies, always
                    slept out in a tent in the rough and in the open. They are quite happy they come
                    in the Pubs and Joe would light his old clay pipe, get it going he would hand it
                    to Annie and there she would puff away. When they were younger they would have a
                    truck to carry their tent, I have seen Joe with two trucks and Annie with her
                    pram. Joe would take one up a hill and walk back to fetch the other. Joe had
                    always been a hard working man he used to work for the farmers peace work and
                    then in winter he would do hedgecutting for the farmers and a bit of scissors
                    grinding and collect rags and bones and then take them into <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName>, Him and Annie were always busy
                    they were both good company wherever they were. They are both now getting on
                    into years, Annie is about 88 and Joe is round about 78, They are now on Daisy
                    Bank where one of Annie's brothers were born. I think his name was Vic. At the
                    present time I do not think they move far from Daisy Bank, Joe came down
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> for his beer and
                    groceries and that is how their life is today. They do have some of their
                    relations come to see them sometimes. The old Daisy Bank has been known for the
                    gipsies all my life and for many years before I remember my Mother used to talk
                    about it year ago. The gipsies in my boy days are different than they are today,
                    I have had some tea with them on Daisy Bank when I was sheep keeping 65 year
                    ago. Annie and Joe are still on Daisy Bank as I write this in 1965 February,</p>
                <p part="N">The time as John Thomas farmed at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> he gave all the boys a nick-name. I will tell you
                    some of the names, Snifter, Inkey Ted, Slough, Howley, Spider, Gilks, Tabby Cat,
                    Peggy, Slipstrings, Waskcoat, Cunning Dofty, Strikup, Bogey, Jack Judge, Blood,
                    Pretty Prince, Tobey, Cockey, Sloper, Betsy King, Skeeno, Beak, Tickey and they
                    all answered by their nick-name, there was also Bdoper, so you see in those days
                    you had always got two names If John Thomas wanted one of you he always called
                    you by your nick-name. x, I remember one Saturday going stone picking up in
                    Stumpet fieid next to Daisy Bank for John Thomas, there was a lot of us, we had
                    6d. for that day's work. The late Jack Ashpole was in charge, he wanted someone
                    to lead the horse, no one wanted to lead the horse to he made no more to do, he
                    tied me to the horses head so I had to lead it and that's how things went on
                    those days. When there was a big flood sometimes the farmers would take you
                    across in a horse and cart, when it was running over the plank. I know the flood
                    to come nearly up to the gate <pb n="30"/> to,the cottage near the school known
                    as Bridge Cottage in my boy days.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>The 1939/45 War.</head>
                <p part="N">There was a lot of young and old took part in this war, the first to go
                    was <persName key="CookP" instant="false" full="yes">Peter Cook</persName>, son
                    of H# J. Cook, the names I will give as far as I can, John Hunt, Jim Hunt, Bert
                    Hulatt, Richard Cumberland, Fred Payne, Tom Rust, Frederick Franklin, Sid
                    Lovell, Harry Dodd, Fred Swales, Bert Cockings, Algy Jones, Alwyn Betts, Charlie
                    Budd, George Marsh, Len Podd, Fred Turner, John Turner, Albert Symons, Don
                    Hulatt, H. Lawson, Peter Stringer, Reg. Barker, Lawrence Fensom, Stan Allen,
                    Terry Longstaff, Ruby Cooper, Gladys Everest, Connie Rust, Edna Betts, Barbara
                    Cumberland. There was also Fred Betts, Joe Hulatt in the Special Police.</p>
                <p part="N">The A.R.P. Post up <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> was in the garage attached to the Grange which was
                    manned each night by various people in the village. Also at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>, the A.R.P. was at Mr. Edwin
                    Robinson's house, that was also manned each night. The lights had to be blacked
                    out in the hours of darkness.</p>
                <p part="N">There was 7 sons of Sir Richard Wells in the forces in 1939/45 war*
                    There was also the Home Guard which took their part in the war from <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> and <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>.</p>
                <p part="N">Farms at <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>.</p>
                <p part="N">Hardwick Farm is farmed by Mr* Kemsley, Hawksfull and Haredine is farmed
                    by Messrs. H. J« Cook and Sons. College Farm is farmed by L. J. Church,
                        <placeName ref="#pl:manor-farm">Manor Farm</placeName> is farmed by Tom
                    Hensman, Brook Farm by Harry Robinson. Willis Farm is farmed by Mrs, Hitchin,
                    Curtis Farm is farmed by Mr|i. Hitchin. Parsons Barn is farmed by Mr. Ibbott,
                    Moor End Farm is farmed by Mr» Ibbott. College Farm is farmed by Miss M.
                    Rootham, <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> Hall Farm is farmed
                    by Mr. Fm Felce. Most of these farms have changed hands this last 30 to 40
                    years, they have been taken over by their sons or some relation of the family*
                    Mr* L* J, Church was taken over from Mr. Wm. Hackney when he came from Turvey.
                    Mr. L. J* Church was married to MMzecfW1** Tongue of Turvey in 1931 and they are
                    still farming there today 1965. They have 3 children and grandchildren.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr. Harry Robinson took over his farm after his father retired, Miss M.
                    Rootham took over her farm on the death of her Father, Mr. R. J* Rootham and is
                    farming there in 1965. Mr# Tom Hensman has the farm when his father retired he
                    now lives at Oakley,</p>
                <pb n="31"/>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head> Felmersham Church.</head>
                <p part="N">It is a fine church in the country and it has a history but I do not
                    intend to go into this, what I propose to do is to write about the things that
                    have happened in the last 70 or 80 years. The steps leading up to the West Door
                    was made in the Squire Green's time according to what I can gather from the
                    elder people. These steps were first came to light through Bishop Wilkson who
                    married the Squire's sister and the Squire was in charge of the work done,
                    according to what I can gather Bishop Wilkson was interned in Felmersham
                    Churchyard. It was usual for the Squire's daughters when they were married to
                    come down the steps. In the summer months the West Ooors would be open and the
                    Squire and his family would enter the Church that way, and the Doors would be
                    open on all special occasions.. The church wardens were- for many years Mr. J.
                    O. Hensman and the late Mr. Arthur Pacey, the church wardens today are Mr. T.
                    Hensman and Mr. L. J. Church, 1965, the Vicar is the Rev. Sidebottom which in
                    due course will no doubt be living among the <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> people when the new vicarage is built.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>Election,</head>
                <p part="N">When there was a General Election in those days there were no Polling
                    Stations in the village, all those that were entitled to a vote had to go to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> School, they used
                    to go in to vote in Horse and Wagon in the daytime, there was only two parties
                    in those days, Liberals and Tories.</p>
                <p part="N">I remember on one occasion the Squire wanted to take my Father to vote,
                    he said Thanks, but I shall go in my Donkey Cart to vote, some of. them were a
                    bit independent in those days. <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> were always a Tory stronghold, what it is today I
                    would not like to say. There is a lot of new people coming to the village to
                    live and there are still a lot of new houses and bungalows going up and in due
                    course it will, I think, become a new village but it will no doufat be the same
                    old village and the beautiful church to go to. I have seen a lot of changes in
                    the village in this last 70 years. It used to be a pleasure to see all the
                    people of the village going to Church and to hear the bells ringing on a Sunday
                    Evening.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>Bells.</head>
                <p part="N">I would now like to say a little about the bell which have been rehung,
                    this was carried out as near as I can gather in 1951 to <pb n="32"/> 1954. There
                    was before 5 bells. The old frames were taken out and rehung in steel frames,
                    the bell when rung, the sound carries a long way owing to being close to the
                    river. The late Sir Richard Wells Bart., who more or less footed the bill on
                    this occasion according to what I been told, he did a lot for the Church, the
                    time he was in residence at the Grange.</p>
                <p part="N">War Memorial.</p>
                <p part="N">This was erected by collection etc. in the village after 1914-18 war, it
                    was unveiled by Mr. Harry Green, the son of the Squire. There was an iron
                    enclosure, it was a usual thing for a rota of men in the two villages to keep
                    the grass cut and keep the Memorial tidy, also the ladies for the month to be
                    responsible for the flowers which was carried out for many years, this used to
                    be in the village magazine. There was also a service held the Sunday nearest to
                    the 11th of November, round the War Memorial about 2o30 all took part. If wet it
                    was held in the church. The iron fence was taken by the Government in the
                    1939/45 war, it was paid for after the war,</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>Radwell*</head>
                <p part="N">Mr. J. Purser who lived at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> when I was married and lived next door to me, he wa«s a
                    man who used to do rush matting, he could do anything, he made baskets, mats,
                    and anything possible he could make with rushes. He used' to cut them in the
                    summer and then he would dry them out, I have seen him many a time drying them
                    out on the green to get them seasoned ready for plaiting them up in the winter
                    and that's how he got his living, he was a crafts* man at his work. There was a
                    lot of this work carried on at Pavenham, these things used to go a long way
                    round the country, of course there is none done about here now the rush plaiting
                    has gone they were artists at the job 30 or 40 year ago* Old Anty of Pavenham
                    used to have the job he could swim like a duck, I seen him many a time, well it
                    seems that this craft has gone for ever, its a great pity as they used to use
                    the rushes which grew in the river and cost very little to produce* Mr, J»
                    Purser has two sons living one at Souldrop and works for Marriotts the Builder
                    at Rushden, the other Eric works at the Stoke Mill for Messrs. Hipwell It Son at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>9 and has been
                    there for a good many years.</p>
                <p part="N">Radwell is what they call a Hamlet, of course, on the Parish <pb n="33"
                    /> Council, There has always been some of the people living at Rad- well on the
                    Council, Mr, W. L. Peck was on the District Council and when he died Mr. R. J.
                    Rootham was elected and now today 1965 Miss M. Rootham has taken up the office,
                    so it has not been out of the Peck family*for years.</p>
                <p part="N">There is 3 farms in <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>
                    occupied by Mr, F. Felce, Miss M. Rootham and Mr. Ibbott. At one t ime Moor End
                    Farm was farmed by a man named Marriott, he also at one time kept the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:swan-inn">Swan Inn</placeName>, after he died Mr* U. L, Peck
                    took over the farm, his wife was the daughter of Mr. Marriott. Mr« Peck was
                    farming at College Farm before he moved to Moor End Farm. Mr, R. J. Rootham
                    married Mr. Peckfs daughter and took over College Farm, after the death of Mr,
                    R« JV Rootham his daughter Miss M« Rootham took over the farm and is there today
                    1965.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr. Felce took over the farm after his father's death and is still
                    farming there today 1965. Mr. Jim Cox farmed at Moor End Farm after the death of
                    his father, Mr .Alfred Cox who bought the farm when it was sold, Mr. La U, Peck
                    farmed there when it was sold, and now Mr© Jim Cox has sold it to Mr. ibbott and
                    farms it today 1965.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a fire about 46 years ago and the two cottages were burnt. It
                    started with an old beam in the chimney, Mr. and Mrs* A« Turner lived there at
                    the time also John Church. The Fire Engine from <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> came to the fire, it was
                    noticed by some men working in the fields off the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> Road. Mr0 A* Turner moved to the
                    house where Mr. and Mrs, Jack Norman lives today 1965, they were uncle and aunt
                    to Mrs, Norman and they brought Mrs, Norman up, as her mother died when she were
                    only a few days old and her brother, Jess my mother his grannie brought him up.
                    The ground where the houses was sold to Mr. Felce and he had a bungalow built by
                    Mr. J. Bamford. Mr. F. Felce lived there for sometime, Mr. Constance lives there
                    today 1965.</p>
                <p part="N">The allotment known as the Pyghtle was, according to what I can gather,
                    in the hands of the Squire and he let it out in allot- ments of 20 poles and
                    when it was sold the late John Betts bought it. It was in the hands of the late
                    Mrs. Betts until she died. It is now owned and let out by Mr* Bert Hulatt. The
                    houses in the lane at one time were owned by the late Mr. Barcock of <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> are now occupied by Mr,
                    Brown, Mr, Wain and Mr, Horsford, all their houses have been altered in these
                    last years. It all points out what can be done with these old properties, its a
                    credit to all <pb n="34"/> those that live there. There is two council houses,
                    the only two in the village. The Swan has had many Landlords in this last 70
                    years, the late John Desborough kept it for a time, Mr. Bowyer kept the Pub in
                    1913 and 1914 and for several years after,there was Mr, Allen kept it for a good
                    few years, also Mr* Stan Cooper and it is now in the hands of Mr. and Mrs.
                    Egan.</p>
                <p part="N">There has been a lot of changes in the village this last 70 years* The
                    Chapel has been closed one time there was services in the after* noon and
                    evening also the children went to Sunday School. The Sun- day School Teacher in
                    the last year was the late Mr* Northwood and his two daughters, Kathleen and
                    Freda which have now moved to East- bourne.. Mr. Sam Barker was horsekeeper for
                    Mr. Alfred Cox, he has worked on the farm for many years and remained in the
                    service until the farm was sold. He still carries on with the allotment, he is
                    87 and still going strong. When Mr. Peck had Moor End Farm he had his horse he
                    used to ride; stolen one night it was found in a field at Kempston.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1938 and 1939 the road up to <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> was being widened when the war broke out and some of
                    the men had to go. It was a narrow lane in those days and the footpath todayused
                    to be part of of the road. The water was put in before the road was widened and
                    the sewer followed it. The electric has been in <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> and Felmersham for a good many years. There used to be
                    wooden planks years ago and theytell me the late Sam Thomas who lived at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> put them down
                    years ago. There were no planks and the ground used to be open to the river
                    years ago. I have no dates to this effect. The stew planks are now concrete and
                    was put down when the wooden ones were not safe to go over.</p>
                <p part="N">The late Mr. John Hulatt used to t???e &amp; foreman and 4#ne contract
                    work for the Council he also had a milk round »t <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> and Rad- well and done jobs
                    for anyone that he could Help, alter his death his son Fred carried on the
                    business until he retired from farming. John Hulatt had 8 children , 4 sons and
                    4 daughters. Fred lived at Radwell and Mrs. Sharman in 1965, at one time he
                    lived in the house where I live, today, where some of his family was born.</p>
                <p part="N">There has been a lot of new bungalows put up in <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> in these last few years, the
                    village is the same more or less as it was years ago and what with the
                    electricity, water and now the sewer we are up to date more than some of the
                    towns today. We have a fairly good bus service. There has always been a lot of
                    fishermen come here to fish and have done for many years and do today in 1965. I
                    think if the <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> Green could
                    talk it could tell some good tales. The Radwell Green comes under the Parish
                    Council. I have in all my life never had any gipsies come to try to .camp on the
                    Green, at any time*</p>
                <pb n="35"/>
                <p part="N"> They have just put new water pipes in the village in 1964, There was a
                    fire at <placeName ref="#pl:college-farm">College Farm</placeName> some years
                    ago. When the canal burst its bank some years ago Mr. Alfred Cox had some of his
                    cattle swim down the river and drown. It came so quick that they jhad no time to
                    get them to higher land. Mr. H. J* Cook had to drive some of his cattle round
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> to get them to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> at the same
                    time.</p>
                <p part="N">The farm house where Mr. E. Robinson lives was built by the Council, it
                    was the first one built in <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>
                    for many years according to what I can gather. The one before that was built by
                    the Harrisons. Mr. E. Robinson farmed there until he retired, his nephew Mr. H*
                    Robinson has taken the land over.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a nam named Mr. Lawson who used to be a Rag and Bone dealer,
                    he was a one armed man but was very active. He could swim and won prizes at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName>. He also played
                    football, he lived in the house where Mr. Webbster lives today. He was captain
                    of the football team and he was umpire for cricket. He took an active part in
                    all sport. He was on the Parish Council for many years. He drove a horse and
                    trolley round the various villages, he had his regular round each day. In his
                    later life him and his son who used to keep the Sun at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> had a motor lorry to go round
                    the villages. Mr. H. G. Lawson had the coal business at Sharnbrook and it still
                    runs in his name* Mr. Lawson senior lost 3 of his sons early in life. There is
                    one son Mr. H. Lawson who lives at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> today 1965. They have two sons and a daughter* One of
                    the sons live in <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> today 1965.
                    Mr, Lawson senior was one time farming at Stevington until he came to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>. He once lived at Dropshort where
                    Mr* H. Robinson lives today. His father kept the Old Boot at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName> for many years*</p>
                <p part="N">At my Father's sale I bought the two fields known as Hilly Pyghtle and
                    Night Close. My son Fred Turner has got a bungalow adjoining Night Close.known
                    as the Five Elms. When the sewer was being put in I used to take my cows up
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> and the trench was open
                    to about 5 or 6 feet deep, it was a bit risky, but we had no accidents, the cows
                    knew there was up the road* After I retired I sold the fields to Mr. R. J.
                    Rootham now taken over by Miss M. Rootham*</p>
                <p part="N">The house which stands on the Green used to belong to the Peak. family,
                    but was sold some years ago to Mr* Prine Everest who was School Master at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> School for some
                    time, and he lived in the house now occupied by Mr* Gi liner, Mr* Lushington
                    lives in the house on the Green 1965*</p>
                <pb n="36"/>
                <p part="N"> The orchard which belongs to the Pecks family and the landlord of the
                    Pub used to rent it off the Peeks family* Then in the later years the Pecks sold
                    it to Messrs, Veils Breweries and now it goes with the Pub. There was also a
                    large barn where they used to thrash wheat and beans in the winter with a
                    thrale, this thrashing barn used to go with the orchard, it was pulled down some
                    years ago. </p>
                <p part="N">There is a house, the last one before you get to the Railway bridge
                    which was built when the widening of the railway was done and this house was
                    built by the Harrisons, after the death, I am given to understand, that
                        <placeName>Mr. Tommy Harrison</placeName> and <placeName>Mr. Jimmy
                        Harrison</placeName>. The sons lived there for sometime, they were both
                    apprentice brick- layers and they worked on the railway bridges when the
                    widening was done. After a time this house was sold to a retired policeman, and
                    then he sold it to the present owner, Mr. Franklin. H e had a caretaker to live
                    there until they came there to live from North- ampton. In the Harrison's time
                    they used to fetch their drinking water from a spring in the pond in Knights
                    Close, in the field opposite the house now owned by <persName>Miss M.
                        Rootham</persName>, when I owned the field I cleaned the pond out and there
                    was the stone steps they used to stand on to get the water. I know this is
                    correct <persName>Jimmy Harrison</persName> told me he had fetched the water
                    many a time. There used to be a stile there he told me, the pond is filled in
                    now*</p>
                <p part="N">In the time when the railway strike was on <persName>Mr.
                        Franklin</persName> was having a little railway track put down in the
                    adjoining fields, the back of the house and there was a Station, a Tunnel and
                    Signal Box, viaduct, just as you would find on the railway. There was a
                    turntable to turn the little steam engine round when required, and it was all up
                    to date. There were carriages and Mr* Franklin's son used to drive the train
                    round on the track and give the children a ride round. There was a lot of people
                    used to come and see the miniature train. You could hear the engine puffing
                    along some distance off. There was two little engines here, but now its all
                    closed, the tunnel fell in, I don't know if the rails are there or not. I helped
                    to make the track, I was in charge of the men when we were getting ready for the
                    rails. My brother carted the rails from <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrookStation">Sharnbrook Station</placeName>, we also
                    carted ashes to make the track. The men who helped got 2/6d. an hour, I paid
                    them and Mr. Franklin paid me. He lived at Northampton at this time, Mr.
                    Franklin he now lives in the house and Mr. Sid Lovell farms the two fields where
                    the track was run round, its not been run now for a long time.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>Radwell Chapel.</head>
                <p part="N">Mr. and Mrs. Lineman was caretakers at the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> Chapel for a. good many years. He
                    always took an active part in the running of the Chapel. He had two daughters,
                    one married a Mr. Stonebanks <pb n="37"/> an&lt;J the other one Mr.
                    Northwood.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr. H. Lineman worked for a man named Marsh, he was grandfather to Mr.
                    Marsh who lives at <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton
                        Ernest</placeName> today 1965. Mr. S. Marsh used to have a horse and cart
                    and used to fetch sheep and cattle etc.that had died. Mr. Lineman used to help
                    skin the animals owing to this he had anthrax and he died from the disease.
                    After then Mr. Northwood came to live in the house. Mrs. Northwood was caretaker
                    and helped with the chapel in her later years. She suffered a lot with
                    arthritis. Mr. Northwood was superintendent for the last years of his life,
                    after his death his two daughters used to manage the chapel and carried on with
                    the Sunday School. They all used to play the organ for the services. Mr.
                    Northwood played for a good many years. Mr. F. Ward was superintendent for spme
                    years also. Mr. John Whitworth he took an active part with the chapel, W. Pecks,
                    Mr. and Mrs. Rootham and many others in the village.</p>
                <p part="N">There was a lot of children used to come to chapel from Felmersham. Mr.
                    Northwood and his two daughters, Kathleen and Freda used to teach at Sunday
                    School and other helpers. The Northwood family took an active part in running
                    the chapel, in the last years until Miss Kathleen and Freda sold their house and
                    went to live at Eastbourne, and now the chapel has been closed since they left
                    and is going to ruin. Its a great pity when you come to think about it and how
                    it was kept up for so many years, I remember going to chapel myself and how we
                    used to look forward to the tea and games we used to have in the afternoon up in
                    Mr* L. W# Peck's field, now occupied by his granddaughter, Miss Rootham,</p>
                <p part="N">There was a good many people from <placeName ref="#pl:bedford"
                        >Bedford</placeName> who used to come and sing at the chapel but that is all
                    finished now. Mr. S, A, Hooker took an active part in the work of the Methodists
                    and preached on many occasions in the <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> Chapel. Also Mr. S* Marsh, they both used to live at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton Ernest</placeName>, Mr. Vilimes
                    from <placeName ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName>, he took an active part
                    at the various chapels round the circuit and many others. They used to have a
                    service at 2,30.and 6.0 o'clock each Sunday/ and there used to be a good
                    gathering assembled until the later years. The chapel was built in 1807. Joseph
                    Swannell was something to do with the building he died in 1817, This Chapel was
                    kept up by collections and it was kept up well and was until it was shut up,
                    approximately 3 years ago, when the chapel was going well, it points out that
                    most in the village took some part in the welfare of the chapel. The parents of
                    the Northwoods are interned in the ground just outside of the chapel burial
                    ground. It was ground which belonged to the <pb n="38"/> late Mr. and Mrs.
                    Northwood. Mr. and Mrs. Northwood and family have always been interested in the
                    welfare of the chapel, I remember on several occasions in the 1939/45 war, I had
                    the pleasure of being in charge of the Home Guard who attended the services.
                    There was always a tea arranged after the anniversary and at Christmas time for
                    the children and the adults. The children got prizes and so on each year and a
                    star for their attendance each Sunday. Most of the children in the village
                    attended the Sunday Chapel School.</p>
                <p part="N">Radwell and <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                    >Felmersham</placeName></p>
                <p part="N">There is at present in <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> bungalows and houses been built in this last 20 years
                    is 17 and two being built up to now. The last one to start is <persName
                        ref="#ps:fensome-lawrence">Mr. L. Fensome</persName> in the ground that
                    used to belong to Miss M. Rootham.</p>
                <p part="N">There are in <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>
                    bungalows and houses been built in the last 25 years to 35 years approximately
                    45 to 55 and there is building going on in several places today. The old
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> ■ will soon be a
                    new one. There is to be built a new vicarage in the field known as <placeName
                        ref="#pl:marriotts-close">Marriotts Close</placeName> where the building
                    is in progress. The house up the <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham-road">Pavenham
                        Road</placeName> known as <placeName ref="#pl:baileys-villas">Baileys
                        Villas</placeName> was built by <persName ref="#ps:bailey">a man of that
                        name</persName>&gt; to used to come down from <placeName ref="#pl:london"
                        >London</placeName> to buy pigs, horses etc. so he bought the ground and had
                    the houses put up to let to the village people and now today they are owned by
                    some of the tenants and the others are let. This man <persName
                        ref="#ps:bailey">Bailey</persName> used to stay at the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:six-ringers-inn">Six Ringers</placeName> when <persName>Mr. J. Thorndyke</persName>
                    was Landlord.</p>
                <p part="N">The house or bungalow up the Carlton Road which were built in the fields
                    known as <placeName>Stumpet Field</placeName> was built by the late Mr.
                    Dewesbury who then lived at <placeName>Underwood Farm</placeName>, <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>. He had it built for his son
                        <persName>Leslie</persName>, who lived there for sometime, he now farms at
                        <persName>Riseley</persName>. <persName>Mr. Dittmer</persName> has the
                    bungalow or house, he bought it when it was sold some years ago. He used to keep
                    pigs and poultry. There was a piece of ground up the <persName>Carlton
                        Road</persName> known as <persName>Cold Harbour</persName>, <persName
                        instant="false" full="yes">Mr. C. Robinson</persName> used to rent it and
                    used to keep some calves in it when I was a boy and worked for him 1 used to put
                    my sheep in there at dinner times, but today <persName>Mr* Swales</persName> who lives in the house
                    which he bought one of Baileys Villas, haa got it and keeps pigs etc. up
                    there.</p>
                <p part="N">There is a footpath which goes in at the bottom of the first hill on the
                    Carlton Road after you leave <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> goes across the field known as Shipens and along the
                    next field to Red Barn and then <pb n="39"/> on,and over the Odell Mill into
                    Odell, I been over it many a time* Carlton Road and Daisy Bank has always been
                    known for gipsies to congregate on and gather in different gangs, but not so
                    many today 1965.</p>
                <p part="N">I have tried to outline the best I can in the two villages in the last
                    years so please excuse me if I left things put. Its a Job to think of all but I
                    wrote it as it came to me, and as far as I know what I wrote is true. It took me
                    approximately 6 weeks on and off and my fingers are getting a bit sore. There is
                    a lot more I could write. There was a man named <persName>Joe Hulatt</persName> who used to live in
                    the house on the Green where <persName>Mr. and Mrs. Lushington</persName> live today. He worked on
                    the railway as a platelayer with my Father. They both worked on there for many
                    years. <persName>Mr. Charles Hulatt Changey</persName> married <persName>Joe
                        Hulatt*s</persName> daughter, and <persName>Mr. J. Hulatt</persName> married
                    the other daughter, so you see two brothers married two sisters. They both lived
                    at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> until Changey moved to
                        <persName>The Row, Felmersham</persName>. <persName>Charles
                        Hulatt</persName>, he ha.d two sons killed in the 1914/18 war <persName>Mr*
                        T. Hulatt</persName> had several sons and daughters. They are about the
                    country somewhere. There is one who lives at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> known as London, his correct name is Herbert Hulatt.
                    There has been a lot of fresh people come in the village this last 15 years. I
                    don't know some of them myself, most of them go out to business.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr. J. Bamford</persName> was Landlord of the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:plough-inn">Plough Inn</placeName> for many years he carried on
                    as a builder and done repair work in the village, in his later years he done
                    repair and etc. for <persName>Captain Starey</persName> at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton Ernest</placeName> until he retired. He
                    now lives in a cottage where the late <persName>Herbert Scrivener</persName>
                    used to live, he was a bricklayer and a handyman.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr.</persName> and <persName>Mrs. Chapman</persName> took over
                    the <placeName ref="#pl:plough-inn">Plough Inn</placeName> and is there today
                    1965. <persName>Mr. Sid Lovell</persName> took over the <placeName ref="#pl:sun-inn">Sun
                        Inn</placeName> after the death of <persName>Mr. H. G. Lawson</persName> and is there today,
                    1965,</p>
                <p part="N">There has been various Landlords at the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:six-ringers-inn">Six Ringers</placeName>, <persName>Mr. G. Hulatt</persName> was
                    Landlord for approximately 12 years. The Swan <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> has had several Landlords, <persName>Mr. Tom
                        Allen</persName>, was Landlord for a good many years. <persName>Mr. Stan
                        Cooper</persName> was Landlord for a few years and now the Landlord is
                        <persName>Mr. Egan</persName>, he has only been Landlord for a few months
                    and is making a lot of improvements.</p>
                <p part="N">Footpaths.</p>
                <p part="N">These footpaths were used years ago, there is one that goes in opposite
                    the <placeName ref="#pl:swan-inn">Swan Inn</placeName> and goes across the
                    fields and comes out at the corner known as The Ashes and along The Ashes and
                    comes up Browlance and over the <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham
                        Road</placeName> and joins the one going up to <pb n="40"/> Turvey. This
                    same footpath used to carry on along the river and come out somewhere where the
                    allotments are at <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName> and on
                    to <placeName ref="#pl:bedford">Bedford</placeName>. There was also at
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>, a bridle path which
                    goes in at Mr. F« Felces farm along to the corner of The Ashes and along to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:pavenham">Pavenham</placeName>. There was hand-gates
                    for the horses to go through, and a stile, for in the old days these were kept
                    up by the Parish Council, the boundaries of <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> and <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> as I can say carry on round by the river, they start in
                    <persName>Mr. J. Hensman's</persName> field not far from Odell Mill, finish up the end of the Ashes,
                    then up to the boundaries by <persName>Major McCullen's</persName> and on to the Carl ton Road and
                    along the Road and join up with <persName>Mr. T. Hensman's</persName> land then over to where we have
                    started from.</p>
                <p part="N">This is as far as I can tell you, there is a footpath goes across to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:sharnbrook">Sharnbrook</placeName> goes in over the
                    bridge and comes out at Sharnbrook.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr. Taylor</persName> who was Landlord at The Sun for several years, he was then a
                    gunsmith and tinsmith. H e was an artist at his work, he was a man who could
                    make anything you wanted and he was a very handyman. H e used to do his work in
                    the building attached to the Sun. He used to do a lot for the farmers to repair
                    the drills etc. After he left he went to live at Carlton, he used to drive a
                    pony and trap to the various jobs he had to do in other villages. I think I am
                    right in saying he was on the Parish Council.</p>
                <p part="N">I was a reporter for the Beds.'Times for <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> and Felmer- sham for several years. <persName>Mr. Pratt</persName> was
                    reporter after me until he left the village. In the village of <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> when anyone had to be buried it was
                    a custom to have 6 bearers and they would change at various times. There was no
                    bier in those days until the village obtained one which is kept in a building in
                    the spinney near the church. The bearers did not get paid much for this job, it
                    was done in those days more or less as your friends as a rule they had bread and
                    cheese with a little beer. I don't think the farmer stopped their wages on these
                    jobs.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr* Sam Barker</persName> the oldest man who was born in the village, he is now 87
                    and has seen many changes in the village. He remembers the <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> planks being put down by <persName>Mr. Sam
                    Thomas</persName>, that was all open to the river before then, and when the flood was out
                    they used to go along the railway to get to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton Ernest</placeName>. He has been on the
                    farm all his life as far as I know. He was horsekeeper for the late <persName>V/. L, Peck</persName>
                    and then when the farm was sold to <persName>Mr. A, Cox</persName> he was horsekeeper for him, and
                    then carried on with the son Jim Cox until the farm was sold. He has been a keen
                    gardener and took a pride in his allotment which he had for many years, he still
                        <pb n="41"/> carries on with his allotment. He also took a pride in his
                    horses and has been a very active man all his life. He lost his wife years ago
                    and his daughter <persName>Mrs. Longstaff</persName> lives with him and looks after him. He has lived
                    in the same house for many years.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mr.</persName> and <persName>Mrs. Barker</persName> had 2 sons, <persName>Fred</persName> and <persName>Reg</persName> and 5 daughters, two
                    daughters live at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> and one
                    son. Both the sons work on the County Council. Fred the oldest son lives at
                    Stagsden, he is foreman on the road.</p>
                <p part="N">The farm at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> known as
                        <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> Hall used to belong to
                    <persName>Mr, Hodge</persName>, and he sold it to <persName>Mr. C. Felce</persName> after his death his son Fred Felce
                    carries on the farm today 1965. There was also at <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>, <persName
                        ref="#ps:surridge-william">Mr. William Surridge</persName>. He was a
                    smallholder and carter. He had several sons and they used to cart stones etc.
                    about for the county council and fetch them from <placeName
                        ref="#pl:sharnbrook-station">Sharnbrook Station</placeName> and tip them
                    in heaps along the road side, ready for when the steam roller came to repair the
                    road. Their son Fred carried on until they went to live at Odell. <persName>Mr. Surridge</persName>
                    their Father lived to be over 90. He was a grand old man and could do any- thing
                    on the land. His son <persName>Fred</persName> still lives at Odell, he is 74* There was the
                    <persName>Desboroughs</persName>, they used to have a small holding and do a bit of carting. Their
                    son <persName>John Desborough</persName> was Landlord of the <placeName ref="#pl:swan-inn">Swann
                        Inn</placeName> for sometime. He married the daughter of the late <persName>John
                    Barker</persName>, sister to <persName>Mr. Sam Barker</persName> who lived at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> today 1965 age 87. There are lots more I could write
                    about <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> but I must stop
                    somewhere. There is such a lot of changes this last 70 years, so we must try and
                    keep up with them the best they can.</p>
                <p part="N">Felmersham and <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> W.I.
                    1965.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Mrs* Wain</persName> President and 19 members of the W.I. to celebrate the Goi.den
                    Jubilee of the National Federation of Womens Institute in 1965. <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> as with W.I. all over England
                    planted a red oak tree. The planting ceremony took place on the roadside near
                    Dropshorti qu TJhuxsday March 11th at 3.0.p.m. The committee appeared! o»i tti|#
                    scene at 9.30 to dig and prepare the hole ready for the tnre^ W be planted. The
                    tree was planted by <persName>Mrs. Cooper</persName> who had be^ifc a» member of the W#I. since it
                    was formed 43 years ago. Ass£afci»x^ her was <persName>Adrian Hunt</persName> from <placeName
                        ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> and Pauline Turner f rom
                    ftac&amp;vell. A large number of people were present including Ike Y%car, Rev.
                    G. Sidebottom. Also the school teachers, Miss Ffecey and <persName>Mrs. Robinson</persName> with the
                    school children and 2 members ©.** the Parish Council, <persName>Mr. T. Hens man</persName> and <persName>Mrs.
                        <pb n="42"/> Kerns ley*</persName> After the planting <persName>Mrs, Wain</persName> the President invited
                    everyone to the school for a cup of tea and biscuits which was served by members
                    of the Committee.</p>
                <p part="N">This is the last page in the book.</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Robert Turner</persName>.</p>
                <p part="N">March, 1965.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 part="N" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <pb n="43"/>
                <head>Grave Diggers Diary 1763 - 1831.</head>
                <p part="N">In the year <date when="1814-01" instant="false">1814 January</date>
                    snow fell and lay until <date when="1814-04-03" instant="false">April
                    3rd</date>. Onions were sold 4d. each.</p>
                <p part="N">In the Parish of <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> there was 38 houses, I went in, my month was never
                    so late before, finished harvest November 8th, wheat was 5/0 a bushel.
                        <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName> Parish Land let at
                    14/0 acre. One rood to the Church, 2 acres to the pooxrfnen and 3 acres to 12
                    widows. 1818 February 16th, began to cut the stone for the 'bridge. May 20th
                    began to build the new bridge. June 13 turned the first arch. June 16th began to
                    make a new bakehouse for <persName>Mr. Brown</persName>. June 27th Turned the second arch. Aug. 3rd
                    Turned the third arch. Aug. 22nd. Turned the 4th arch. Oct. 6th. Turned the 5th
                    arch.</p>
                <p part="N">1819. January 5th. <persName>Richard Wills</persName> is 68. Married <persName>Ann Archer</persName> she is 26
                    years old. 1819 January a great flight of doves settled on <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> Chapel between 6 and 7 at night.
                    February 24th the first and last arch fell down, on October 14th they turned the
                    second arch that fell down 1820. After one year and 19 weeks labour they
                    finished the broken bridge. July 8th they had such a flood that all the arches
                    of the bridge was covered. •</p>
                <p part="N"><persName>Thomas Barker</persName> 72 years of age went avay for debauchery with <persName>Mary Ann
                    Drage</persName> 14 years of age. <persName>Thomas Barker</persName> came back home again in 1823, January 26th.
                    February 4th mutton was 4d, 1b. 1924 <persName>John Brooks</persName> was transported beyond the seas
                    for 7 years. Aug. 10th <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>
                    Feast.Tuesday, morning in the hours of 2 she would not hold her peace, this was
                    <persName>Dickens Prigmore</persName> and <persName>his wife</persName>, but she was at fault. On Sunday had risen up upon
                    the Irish men all. our men had bludgeons, but our farmers, <persName>Joseph
                        Payne</persName>, <persName>Sam Swannell</persName>, <persName>William
                        Swannell</persName>, <persName>Joseph Swannell</persName>, made peace. New
                    house was built at <placeName ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName>, Moor End
                    October 3rd, open 1825. <persName>Robert Cost in</persName> and <persName>James Hulatt</persName> sent to prison for
                    stealing sheep, Feb 13, Joseph Payn® barn at Hardwick was wilfully set on fire,
                    <persName>Benjamin Parsons</persName> sent to gaol, beaten <persName>Joseph Wills</persName> one of the watchers at the
                    fire.</p>
                <p part="N">March 16th <persName>George Costin</persName>, <persName>Dickens
                        Prigmore</persName> was sent to jail for setting fire to Mr. Payne's barn,
                    Hardwick and stealing sheep. July 15th <persName>George Costin</persName> and
                        <persName>Frances Hulatt</persName> was condemned to be hanged but was
                    transported for life. <persName>Dickens Prigmore</persName> turned Kings
                    evidence.</p>
                <pb n="44"/>
                <p part="N">King George IV died June 26th 1830, was buried on St. Swithans day at
                    10.0 o'clock and I knolled the bell 14 hours in the time,</p>
                <p part="N">February 8th a great flood and 2 bakers went to Milton Ernest and a man,
                    a blacksmith, named Prudden to work at Bletsoe till night and he went to
                        <placeName ref="#pl:milton-ernest">Milton Ernest</placeName> to come home
                    with the two bakers, and they came down to flood to <placeName
                        ref="#pl:radwell">Radwell</placeName> bridge. The flood overturned the
                    cart. Smith got out of the cart to swim but he was never found. The two bakers
                    got out and the horse and cart was carried into the Perrys Meadows, it was never
                    known in the old age, the man's name was Harpen or Orpin. This is still talked
                    in <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham">Felmersham</placeName>.</p>
                <p part="N">October 31st, great flood that ever was known it drove the wall down
                    from the bridge 1823. In October it started snowing and rained 1829 for 89 days
                    and very cold 1830. On January 10th Joseph set sail to the West Indies. Nov.
                    25th snowed and it lay on the ground until the lay on the ground until March
                    12th 1830.</p>
                <p part="N">This I have copied out of the Grave Digger's Diary I thought you would
                    like to read it with the history of <placeName ref="#pl:felmersham"
                        >Felmersham</placeName> and <placeName ref="#pl:radwell"
                        >Radwell</placeName> I have written*</p>
                <p part="N">R.T.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
